<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some considerations about the reconcileableness of reason and religion by T.E., a lay-man ; to which is annex'd by the publisher, a discourse of Mr. Boyle, about the possibility of the resurrection.</title>
            <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E42A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11733674</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11733674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48436</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29027)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48436)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 15:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some considerations about the reconcileableness of reason and religion by T.E., a lay-man ; to which is annex'd by the publisher, a discourse of Mr. Boyle, about the possibility of the resurrection.</title>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691. Some physico-theological considerations about the possibility of the resurrection.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], xviii, [2], 126, [6], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for H. Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"T.E." is identified as Robert Boyle.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Boyle's Discourse appears as Wing B4042 at reel 15:15 and 385:11b, and is cataloged separately.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library and Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Entry for B4024 cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith and reason --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Resurrection --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48436:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48436:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME CONSIDERATIONS ABOUT The Reconcileableneſs OF REASON AND RELIGION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> T.E. <hi>A LAY-MAN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is annex'd by the Publiſher,</hi> A Diſcourſe of Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> ABOUT THE POSSIBILITY OF THE RESURRECTION.</p>
            <q>Homines abſque rerum diſcrimine incredulos eſſe, ſummae eſt imperitiae. <bibl>
                  <hi>Verulam. in Novo Organo.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>H. Herringman,</hi> at the <hi>Anchor</hi> in the <hi>Lower Walk</hi> of the <hi>New Exchange.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48436:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48436:2"/>
            <head>THE Publiſher TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THeſe Conſiderations about <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd by a Perſon of an excellent <hi>Genius</hi> and Ability to conſider the Nature of the things he is wont to diſcourſe upon, being fallen into my hands, nor being forbidden to publiſh them; I thought the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſo weighty, and the way of handling it both ſo diſcreet and ſolid, that I could not forbear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending it to the Preſs, being fully perſuaded, the Publick in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, as well as all Perſons in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular that are concern'd for the ſafety both of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:48436:3"/>and conſequently for their Dignity as they are <hi>Men,</hi> and their Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as they are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> will find ſufficient cauſe to be pleaſed with the publication of it. To which I have nothing to add but that, whereas at the beginning of the following Diſcourſe there is mention made of its being to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of <hi>Two</hi> Parts; one, to ſhew, that a Chriſtian <hi>need</hi> not lay aſide his Reaſon; and the other, that he is <hi>not commanded</hi> to do ſo: The Author thought fit to keep that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which concern'd the latter, from <hi>now</hi> accompanying the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which ſeems the moſt ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and likelieſt to make impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on that ſort of Perſons, whom he chiefly deſigns to perſuade.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:48436:3"/>
            <head>THE Preface.</head>
            <p>'TIs the juſt Grief, and frequent Complaint of thoſe that take to heart the Concerns of <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that they ſee it now more furiouſly aſſaulted and ſtudiouſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd than ever, not only by the vicious Lives of Men, but by their licentious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes. I know, there have been Vices in the World, as long as there have been Men: And 'tis an obſervation as old as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>7.10.</hi> That Men are apt to look upon their own Times as worſe than thoſe that preceded them. And becauſe I remember too, that in reciting this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint he diſapproves it; I ſhall not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, whether other Ages have been leſs faulty than this we live in: But this I think I may ſay with as much Truth as Grief, that, among us here in <hi>England,</hi> the Times, to which our memory can reach, have been leſs guilty, than the preſent Time is, of a <hi>ſpreading</hi> and <hi>bold</hi> Profaneneſs. For, though many allow'd themſelves to
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:48436:4"/>court Gold, and Cups, and Miſtreſſes, little leſs than now they do; yet theſe were ſtill acknowledg'd to be Faults even by thoſe that committed them, and the <hi>Precepts</hi> and the <hi>Counſels</hi> of Religion were neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or diſobeyed, but not their <hi>Authority</hi> thrown off or affronted; Men retaining yet ſuch a kind of reſpect for Her, as the elder Son in the Parable did for his Father, when, receiving a command from him to go and work in his Vineyard, he anſwer'd, <hi>I go Sir,</hi> though <hi>he went not,</hi> Mat. <hi>21.30.</hi> But now too many of the Vicious do not only ſcandalouſly violate the Laws of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but queſtion the Truth, and deſpiſe the very Name of it. They rather chooſe to imitate the Rebels in the other Parable, and ſay of Religion what they did of their lawful King, when they inſolently declar'd, <hi>that they would not have him to reign over them,</hi> Luke <hi>19.14.</hi> They ſeek not to hide their ſins like <hi>Adam,</hi> but think either to cover or protect all others by that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all, <hi>Impiety;</hi> and, inſtead of cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſcience into ſilence, (as ſinners, not impudent, are wont to do,) by deceitful promiſes of repenting hereafter of their ſins, they endeavour to ſtifle or depoſe it, by maintaining, that <hi>Repentance</hi> is a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, and <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought not
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:48436:4"/>to be look'd on as the Vicegerent of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whoſe very Exiſtence or Providence they diſpute.</p>
            <p>And that which more troubled me, and made me moſt apprehend the ſpreading of this Impiety, was, that it was propagated in a new way, that made me fear, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments not only of vulgar Preachers, but even of learned Divines themſelves, would be much leſs fit than formerly to give a check to its progreſs. For, till of late, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of our Infidels did, either as Philolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, queſtion the Hiſtorical part of the Scriptures, and perhaps cavil at ſome of the Doctrines; or, if they employed Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Arguments, as <hi>Pomponatius</hi> and <hi>Vaninus</hi> did, they borrow'd them from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> or the Peripatetick School. And against both theſe ſorts of Adverſaries, the learneder Champions of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſuch as <hi>Vives, Mornay,</hi> and <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> had furniſh'd Divines with good and proper Weapons. For, the Historical part of the Scriptures, and eſpecially the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, were ſtrongly confirmable by competent Teſtimonies, and other Moral Proofs, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in their kind. And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> being himſelf a dark and dubious Writer, and his Followers being on that account divided into Sects and Parties, which for the moſt
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:48436:5"/>part had nothing to alledge but his ſingle Authority, 'twas not difficult to anſwer the Arguments drawn from the Peripatetick Philoſophy; and, if that could not have been done, it had not been difficult to reject the Doctrines themſelves as falſe or preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. But our <hi>new Libertines</hi> take an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other and ſhorter way, (though I hope it will not be a more proſperous one,) to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine Religion. For, not troubling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>examine</hi> the Hiſtorical or Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal parts of Chriſtian Theology, in ſuch a way as <hi>Jews, Pagans, Mahometans,</hi> would do; Theſe deny thoſe very Principles of Natural Theology, wherein the Chriſtian, and thoſe other differing, Religions agree, and which are <hi>ſuppos'd</hi> in almoſt all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, that pretend to Revelation, namely, the Exiſtence and Providence of a Deity, and a Future State (after this life is ended.) For, theſe Libertines own themſelves to be ſo upon the account of the <hi>Epicurean,</hi> or other <hi>Mechanical,</hi> Principles of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, and therefore to preſs them with the Authorities wont to be employ'd by Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, is improper, ſince they are ſo far from paying any reſpect to the venerable Fathers of the Church, that they ſlight the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Heathen Philoſophers themſelves, judging no Writers worthy of that name,
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:48436:5"/>but thoſe that, like <hi>Leucippus, Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Epicurus,</hi> &amp;c. explicate things by Matter and Local Motion; and therefore 'tis not to be expected, that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence any more the Peripatetick Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Scotus</hi> or <hi>Aquinas,</hi> than the <hi>Homilies</hi> of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> or St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom;</hi> and to give <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf the Title of <hi>The Philoſopher,</hi> were enough to make ſome of them conclude the Aſcriber were <hi>no Philoſopher.</hi> And this, by the way, may excuſe me for not having brought into the following Papers the Sentences of the <hi>Fathers</hi> or the <hi>Moraliſts,</hi> or the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or any of the <hi>School-Philoſophers,</hi> which I ſhould have declin'd to employ, though my frequent removes from place to place, when I was writing theſe Papers, had not deny'd me the convenience of a Library.</p>
            <p>Things being at this paſs, though the Title of this Diſcourſe acknowledges the Author of it to be a <hi>Layman;</hi> yet I ſhall not beg pardon for the enſuing Papers as for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment upon the Eccleſiaſticks. For beſides that, though I know ſome Functions, yet I know no Truths, of Religion, that have the peculiarity of the <hi>Shew-bread</hi> under the Law, <hi>Mat. 12.4.</hi> with which it was lawful only for the Prieſts to meddle; I
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:48436:6"/>will not ſo far miſtruſt the Charity of Churchmen, as not to ſuppoſe, that they will rather thank than blame any man, that being not altogether a ſtranger to this warfare, offers them his aſſiſtance againſt the common Enemy in ſo important a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and ſo great a danger. The Fathers, and other Divines, being wont to compare the Church Militant to a ſhip, 'twill not be an improper extenſion of the Compariſon, to ſay, that, when the Veſſel is threatned with ſhipwrack, or boarded by Pyrates, it may be the Duty not only of profeſs'd Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but any private Paſſenger, to lend his helping hand in that common danger. And I wiſh, I were as ſure, that my endeavors will prove ſucceſsful, as I am, that ſuch Churchmen as I moſt eſteem will think them neither needleſs nor unſeaſonable. Nay, perhaps my being a Secular perſon, may the better qualifie me to work on thoſe I am to deal with, and may make my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, though not more ſolid in themſelves, yet more prevalent with men that uſually (though how juſtly, let them conſider,) have a particular pique at the Clergy, and look with prejudice upon whatever is taught by men, whoſe intereſt is advantag'd by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what they teach believed. And I was the more invited not to be a meer Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:48436:6"/>or a lazy Deplorer of the danger I ſaw Religion in, becauſe it ſeem'd not unlikely, that <hi>Philoſophical Infidels,</hi> as they would be thought, would be leſs tractable to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, though never ſo good Humaniſts and Antiquaries, than to a perſon that reaſons with them upon their own grounds, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with them in their own way, having had a ſomewhat more than ordinary curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to acquaint himſelf with the <hi>Epicurean</hi> and <hi>Carteſian</hi> Principles, and exerciſe himſelf in that Philoſophy, which is very converſant with things Corporeal, and ſtrives to explain them by <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and ſhakes off all Authority (at leaſt that is not infallible.) <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſuch Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as theſe, I comply'd with an occaſion I had of ſolemnly asking <hi>Reaſon</hi> the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, that <hi>Joſhua</hi> once ask'd the Angel that appear'd to him in the Plains of <hi>Jericho, Art thou for us, or for our Adverſaries? Joſh. 5.14;</hi> and of committing to Paper thoſe thoughts that ſhould occur to me on that Subject. And this I the rather did, that I might thereby as well contribute to my own ſatisfaction as to that of my Friends. For, as I think, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that belongs to this life, that ſo much deſerves our ſerious care as what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us when we are paſt it; ſo I
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:48436:7"/>think, that he who takes a reſolution either to embrace or reject ſo important a thing as <hi>Religion,</hi> without ſeriouſly examining why he does it, may happen to make a good Choice, but can be but a bad Chooſer. And that I might not exclude, by too early a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, thoſe things, that, for ought I knew, might hereafter be pertinent and uſeful, I threw my Reflections into one Book, as into a Repoſitory, to be kept there only as a heap of differing materials, that, if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd worth it, they might be afterwards review'd, and ſorted, and drawn into an orderly Diſcourſe. But, before I began to do what I intended, a ſucceſſion of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, (wherewith 'twould not be proper to trouble the Reader,) quite diverted me to employments of a very diſtant na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo that theſe Papers, being thrown by, did for divers years lie neglected, with many others, till at length the perſon, for whoſe peruſal I in the firſt place deſign'd them, join'd with ſome other intelligent Friends to urge me to ſend them abroad, though I was not in a condition to give them the finiſhing ſtrokes, or ſo much as to fill up ſeveral of the Blanks, my haſte had made me leave to be ſupply'd when I ſhould be at leiſure. And indeed, notwithſtanding the juſt averſneſs I had from letting a piece ſo
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:48436:7"/>incomplete and uncorrected appear in this Critical Age; yet the hopes, they confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave me, that this piece, ſuch as it is, might not be unacceptable nor uſeleſs, were not, I confeſs, altogether groundleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Novelty</hi> being a thing very acceptable in this age, and particularly to the perſons I am to deal with, to whom perhaps 'tis none of the leaſt endearments of their Errors, I deſpair not, that 'twill ſomewhat recommend theſe Papers, to which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to commit not Tranſcripts of what I thought they may have already met with in Authors, but ſuch conſiderations, as a <hi>ſerious attention,</hi> and the <hi>nature of the things</hi> I treated of, ſuggeſted to me; ſo that moſt of the things will perhaps be thought new; and ſome few things coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with what they may have elſewhere met with, may poſſibly appear rather to have been ſuggeſted by conſidering the ſame ſubjects, to other Authors and to me, than to have been borrowed by me of them. But ſome few things, I confeſs, I employ, that were commonly enough employed before, and I hope, I may in that have done Religion no diſſervice; For having taken notice, that ſome of the more familiar Arguments had a real force in them, but had been ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warily
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:48436:8"/>propoſed as to be lyable to exceptions that had diſcredited them; I made it my care, by propoſing them more cautiouſly, to prevent ſuch objections, which alone kept their force from being apparent.</p>
            <p>I was not unmindful of the great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage this Tract was likely to undergo, partly for want of a more curious method, and partly becauſe my other occaſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that if I Publiſhed it at all, it muſt be left to come abroad uupoliſh'd and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiſhed. But though this Inconvenience had like to have ſuppreſt this Diſcourſe; yet the force of it was much weaken'd by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that this immethodical way of Writing would beſt comply with what was deſigned and pretended in this Paper, which was, not to write a compleat Treatiſe of the Subject of it; but only to ſuggeſt about it ſome of thoſe many conſiderations, that (queſtionleſs) might have occurred to (what I do not pretend to) an Enlightned and Penetrating Intellect. And the Loadſtone, divers of whoſe <hi>Phenomena</hi> are mention'd in the body of this little Tract, ſuggeſted ſomewhat to me in reference to the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it, by exciting in me a hope, that, if this Diſcourſe have any thing near as much Truth as I endeavour'd to furniſh
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:48436:8"/>it with, that Truth will have its operation upon ſincere Lovers of it, notwithſtanding the want of regularity in the method: As a good Loadſtone will not, by being rough and rudely ſhap'd, be hinder'd from exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing its Attractive and Directive powers upon Steel and Iron.</p>
            <p>As for the Style, I was rather ſhy than ambitious of bringing in the <hi>Thorns</hi> of the School-men or the <hi>Flowers</hi> of Rhetoric: For, the latter, though they had of their own accord ſprung up under my Pen, I ſhould have thought improper to be imployed in ſo ſerious and Philoſophical a Subject: And as to the former, I declin'd them, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance to the humor of my Infidels, who are generally ſo prejudic'd againſt the School-men, that ſcarce any thing can be preſented them with more diſadvantage than in a Scholaſtick dreſs; and a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration will ſcarce paſs for a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with ſome of them, if it be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into a Syllogiſm in mode and figure. That therefore, which I chiefly aim'd at in my expreſſions, was ſignificancy and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that my Reader might ſee, that I was willing to make him judge of the ſtrength of my Arguments, and would not put him to the trouble of divining in what it lay,
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:48436:9"/>nor inveigle him by ornaments of ſpeech, to think it greater than it was. I was alſo led by my Reaſon, as well as by my Inclination, to be careful not to rail at my Infidels: And though I have ſome cauſe to think, that many of them had their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings debauch'd by their lives, and were ſeduc'd from the Church not by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agoras</hi> or <hi>Pyrrho,</hi> but by <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus;</hi> yet I treat them as ſuppoſing them to be what they would be thought, Friends to Philoſophy: And being but a <hi>Layman,</hi> I did not think my ſelf obliged to talk to them as out of a Pulpit, and threaten them with Damnation unleſs they believ'd me, but choſe to diſcourſe to them rather as to erring <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> than Wicked wretches.</p>
            <p>This moderation that I have us'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, will, I hope, induce them to grant me two or three reaſonable requeſts; whereof the <hi>firſt</hi> ſhall be, that they would not make a final judgment of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers till they have perus'd them quite through; eſpecially having in their Eye what is declar'd in the <hi>Preamble,</hi> where both the deſign and ſcope of the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and what it does not pretend to, is expreſt. The <hi>next</hi> thing I am to requeſt of them, and my Readers, is, that they
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:48436:9"/>would not have the meaner thoughts of my Arguments for not being propos'd with the confidence, wherewith many Writers are wont to recommend weaker proofs. For I wrote to intelligent Men, and, in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch, I never obſerv'd that a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration ceas'd to be thought one for being modeſtly propos'd; but I have often known a good Argument loſe of its credit by the invidious Title of a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And I muſt further beg my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to eſtimate my <hi>Deſign</hi> in theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers by the <hi>Title</hi> of them, in which I do not pretend to make Religion trample upon Reaſon, but only to ſhew the <hi>Reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs</hi> of the one to the other, and the friendly agreement between them. I am a perſon, who looking upon it as my Honour and Happineſs to be both a <hi>Man,</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> would neither write nor believe any thing, that might misbecome me in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe two capacities. I am not a Chriſtian, becauſe it is the Religion of my Countrey, and my Friends; nor, becauſe I am a ſtranger to the Principles either of the <hi>Atomical,</hi> or the <hi>Mechanical</hi> Philoſophy. I admit no mans Opinions in the whole lump, and have not ſcrupled, on occaſion, to own diſſents from the generality of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:48436:10"/>men, whether Philoſophers or Divines: And when I chooſe to travel in the beaten Road, 'tis not becauſe I find 'tis the Road, but becauſe I judge 'tis the Way. Poſſibly I ſhould have much fewer Adverſaries, if all thoſe that yet are ſo, had as atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and impartially conſider'd the Points in Controverſie as I have endeavour'd to do. They would then, 'tis like, have ſeen, that the Queſtion I handle, is not whether Rational Beings ought to avoid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Aſſents, but whether, when the Hiſtorical and other Moral Proofs clearly ſway the Scales in favour of Chriſtianity, we ought to flie from the Difficulties that attend the granting of a Deity and Providence, to Hypotheſes, whether Epicurean or others, that are themſelves incumber'd with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding Difficulties: On which account I conceive, that the Queſtion between them and me is not, whether They, or I, ought to ſubmit to Reaſon (for we both agree in thinking our ſelves bound to that;) but whether They or I ſubmit to Reaſon the fullieſt inform'd, and leaſt byaſs'd by Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, Vanity, or Secular Intereſt.</p>
            <p>I reverence and cheriſh Reaſon as much, I hope, as any of them; but I would have Reaſon practiſe Ingenuity as well as Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:48436:10"/>and both induſtriouſly pry into things <hi>within</hi> her ſphere, and frankly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (what no Philoſopher that conſiders will deny) that there are ſome things <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond</hi> it. And in theſe it is, that I think it as well her Duty to admit Revelation, as her Happineſs to have it propos'd to her: And, even as to Revelations themſelves, I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Reaſon to judge <hi>of</hi> them, before ſhe judges <hi>by</hi> them. The following Papers will, I hope, manifeſt, that the main dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt my Adverſaries and me is, that they judge upon particular Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Objections, and I, upon the whole matter. And to conclude; <hi>as</hi> I make uſe of my Watch to eſtimate Time, when ever the Sun is abſent or clouded, but when he ſhines clearly forth, I ſcruple not to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and adjuſt my Watch by his Beams caſt on a Dial; <hi>ſo,</hi> wherever no better Light is to be had, I eſtimate Truth by my own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but where Divine Revelation can be conſulted, I willingly ſubmit my fallible Reaſon to the ſure Informations afforded by Celeſtial Light.</p>
            <p>I ſhould here put an end to this long Preface, but that to the things, which have been ſaid concerning what I have written of my own, I ſee 'tis requiſite that I add a
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:48436:11"/>few words about what I quote from other Writers; eſpecially becauſe in this very Preface I mention my having intended to entertain my Friend with my own Thoughts. Of the Citations therefore that my Reader will meet with in the following Papers, I have this Account to give him: <hi>(1.)</hi> That I had written the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Diſtinctions to which they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, before I met with theſe cited Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which I afterwards inſerted in the Margent, and other vacant places of my Epiſtle. <hi>(2.)</hi> That theſe Paſſages are not borrow'd from Books that treat of the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion, or of Chriſtian Theology at all, but are tak'n from Authors that write of Philoſophical Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and are by me apply'd to Mine, which are uſually very diſtant from Theirs. <hi>(3.)</hi> If you then ask me, why I make uſe of their Authority, and did not content my ſelf with my own Ratiocinations? I have this to Anſwer; that my deſign being to convince another who had no reaſon to look upon my Authority, and whom I had cauſe to ſuſpect to have entertain'd ſome prejudices againſt any Reaſons that ſhould come from one that confeſſedly aim'd at the defending of the Chriſtian Religion, I thought it very proper
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:48436:11"/>and expedient to let him ſee, that divers of the ſame things (for ſubſtance,) that I deliver'd in favour of that Religion, had been taught as Philoſophical Truths by <hi>Men</hi> that <hi>were not</hi> profeſs'd Divines, and <hi>were</hi> Philoſophers, and ſuch ſtrict Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts too, as to be extraordinarily care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful not to take any thing into their Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy upon the account of Revelation. And on this occaſion let me obſerve to you, that there are ſome Arguments, which being clearly built upon Senſe or evident Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, need borrow no Aſſiſtance from the Refutation of any of the Propoſers or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provers, and may, I think, be fitly enough compar'd to Arrows ſhot out of a Croſs-Bow, or Bullets ſhot out of a Gun, which have the ſame ſtrength, and pierce equally, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be diſcharg'd by a Child, or a ſtrong Man. But then, there are other Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocinations, which either <hi>do,</hi> or are <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd</hi> to depend, in ſome meaſure, upon the judgment and skill of thoſe that make the Obſervations whereon they are grounded, and their Ability to diſcern Truth from Counterfeits, and Solid things from thoſe that are but Superficial ones: And theſe may be compar'd to Arrows ſhot out of a Long-Bow, which make much the greater
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:48436:12"/>impreſſion, by being ſhot by a ſtrong and skilful Archer. And therefore when we queſtion, what Doctrines ought or ought not to be thought Reaſonable, it do's not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle facilitate a Propoſitions appearing (not Contrary, but) Conſonant to Reaſon, that 'tis look'd upon as ſuch by thoſe that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Maſters of that Faculty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:48436:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48436:13"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 38. line 6. read <hi>of</hi> for <hi>or.</hi> ib. l. 9. dele all that is contained in that whole parentheſis. ib. l. 19. The diſcourſe, beginning in that line with the words, <hi>if no body,</hi> and ending p. 43. l. 7. with the words, <hi>contiguous and moved,</hi> is to be included between two ſigns of a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, []. P. 43. l. 18. del. Parentheſis before the words, <hi>as were,</hi> and put it l. 20. before the word, <hi>and.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48436:13"/>
                  <head>SOME <hi>CONSIDERATIONS</hi> ABOUT The Reconcileableneſs OF REASON &amp; RELIGION.</head>
                  <head>The Firſt Part.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to what you write in your Friends name, near the bottom of the firſt page of your Letter, perhaps I ſhall not miſtake, if I gueſs, that, when He ſeems but to propoſe a <hi>Queſtion,</hi> he means an <hi>Objection;</hi> and covertly intimates, that I, among many others, am reduc'd to that paſs, that to embrace our <hi>Religion,</hi> we muſt renounce our <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and conſequently, that to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> one muſt ceaſe to be a <hi>Man,</hi> and much more, leave off being a <hi>Philoſopher.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48436:14"/>
                  <p>What liberal Conceſſions ſoever ſome others have been pleas'd to make on ſuch an Occaſion as this, they do not concern me; who, being ask'd but my own Opinion, do not think my ſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible for that of others. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that I may frame my Anſwer ſo, as to meet both with the obvious ſenſe of the Queſtion, and the intimated mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Him that propoſes it, I ſhall roundly make a <hi>Negative</hi> Reply, and ſay, <hi>That I do not think, that a Chriſtian, to be truly ſo, is oblig'd to forego his Reaſon; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by denying the Dictates of right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or by laying aſide the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I doubt not but this Anſwer is differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enough from what your Friend ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects; and perhaps thoſe Grants, that have been made by the Indulgence or Inadvertency of many perſons, eminent for being Pious or Learned, may make you your ſelf ſtartle at this Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And therefore, though you will not, I know, expect an Anſwer to what Objections your Friend may make, ſince he has expreſs'd but what He thinks ought to be a Chriſtian's Opinion, not what he has to object againſt what is ſo; yet, to ſatisfie thoſe Scruples that you your ſelf may retain, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48436:14"/>(but with the Brevity that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Letter) to acquaint you <hi>by themſelves,</hi> with <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>Poſitive</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements, that have led me to this Opinion, and <hi>interweave ſome others,</hi> in anſwering the chief Objections that I think likely to be made againſt it.</p>
                  <p>And this Preamble, ſhort as it is, will, I hope, ſerve to keep you from miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my deſign; which, as you may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from what I have intimated, is not to give you the <hi>poſitive</hi> proofs of the Chriſtian Religion (which is not here to be expected from a bare Defendant,) but to give you ſome <hi>Specimens</hi> of ſuch general Conſiderations, as may proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhew, that the Matter (or Eſſential Doctrines) peculiar to the Chriſtian Religion, is not ſo repugnant to the Principles of true Natural Philoſophy, as that to believe them, a Man muſt ceaſe to act like a Rational Man, any more than he would be oblig'd to do by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing other Religions, or ev'n the Tenents that have been held without diſparagement to their Intellectuals, by the meer Philoſophers themſelves; which laſt Clauſe I add, becauſe I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, you do not expect, that I ſhould be ſollicitous to vindicate the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48436:15"/>belief of a Deity from being Irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional; ſince, beſides that perhaps your Friend would think himſelf affronted to be dealt with as an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> without having profeſs'd himſelf one, the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of a Deity blemiſhes the Chriſtian's Reaſon no more, than it do's that of Men of all Religions, not to ſay of all Mankind; and imports no other contradiction to Reaſon, than what has been judg'd to be none at all by the Greateſt, if not by all, of the Philoſophers that were fam'd for being guided by Reaſon (without Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.) And I ſhall venture to add (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the by) that, <hi>as</hi> I do not for my own part think the Atheiſts Philoſophical Objections (if your Friend had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd them) to be near ſo conſiderable for weight or number, as not only thoſe few that deny a God, but many of thoſe that believe one, are wont to think; <hi>ſo</hi> the Chriſtian is not reduc'd, as is ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd, to make the Being of a Deity a meer <hi>Poſtulatum;</hi> ſince, beſides the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Arguments he can alledge in common with the beſt Champions for a Deity, he has a peculiar Hiſtorical Proof that may ſuffice; the Miracles perform'd by Chriſt and his followers being ſuch,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48436:15"/>that if the matter of Fact can be (as it may be) well evinc'd, they will not only prove the reſt of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but in the firſt place, That there muſt be a God to be the Author of them.</p>
                  <p>But though of the two things which my deſign obliges me to Endeavor the making good of, the moſt Natural order ſeems to be, that I ſhould <hi>firſt</hi> ſhew, That no Precepts of Chriſtianity do <hi>command</hi> a Man to lay aſide his Reaſon in matters of Religion; and <hi>then,</hi> That there is nothing in the Nature of the Chriſtian Doctrine it ſelf that makes a Man <hi>need</hi> to do ſo; Yet I think it not amiſs in treating of theſe two Subjects to invert the Order, and <hi>firſt</hi> conſider that difficulty which is the Principal, and which your Friend and You jointly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have my thoughts of; namely, <hi>Whether there be a neceſſity for a Chriſtian to deny his Reaſon?</hi> And <hi>then</hi> we ſhall proceed to examine, Whether, though he <hi>need</hi> not diſclaim his Reaſon, it be nevertheleſs his <hi>Duty</hi> ſo to do?</p>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48436:16"/>
                     <head>SECT. I.</head>
                     <p>To proceed then to the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that make up the former Part of this Epiſtle; <hi>I ſhall in the</hi> firſt <hi>place di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt that which the Chriſtian Religion it ſelf teaches, and that which is taught by this or that Church or Sect of Chriſtians, and much more by this or that particular Divine or Schoolman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I Need not perſuade you, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but know it ſo well already, that there are many things taught about the Attributes and Decrees of God, the Myſteries of the Trinity, and Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and divers other Theological Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, about which not only private Chriſtians, but Churches of Chriſtians do not at all agree. There are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Men, whoſe Ambition, or Boldneſs, or Self-conceit, or Intereſt, leads them to obtrude upon others, as parts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Things that are not only Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but oftentimes Enemies to it. And there are others, who out of an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet Devotion are ſo ſollicitous to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Number and the Wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Myſteries, that, to hear them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48436:16"/>propoſe and Diſcourſe of things, one would judge, that they think it is the office of <hi>Faith,</hi> not to elevate, but to trample upon <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and that things are then fitteſt to be believ'd, when they are not clearly to be proved or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. And indeed, when on the one ſide I conſider the charitable deſign of the Goſpel, and the candid ſimplicity that ſhines in what it propoſes, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and on the other ſide, what ſtrange and wild Speculations and Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences have been father'd upon it, not only in the Metaphyſical Writings of ſome Schoolmen, but in the Articles of Faith of ſome Churches; I cannot but think, that if all theſe Doctrines are parts of the Chriſtian Religion, the Apoſtles, if they were now alive, would be at beſt but <hi>Catechumini;</hi> and I doubt not but many of the nice Points that are now much valued and urg'd by ſome, would be as well diſapproved by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as by <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> and ſhould be as little entertain'd by an Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, as a Rigid Philoſopher. I do not therefore allow all <hi>that</hi> for Goſpel, which is taught for ſuch in a Preachers Pulpit, or ev'n a Profeſſors Chair. And therefore, if Scholaſtick Writers, of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48436:17"/>what Church ſoever, take the liberty of impoſing upon the Chriſtian Religion their Metaphyſical Speculations, or any other meerly humane Doctrines, as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith, I who, not without ſome Examination, think Metaphyſicks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not to have been for the moſt part over-well underſtood, and apply'd, ſhall make bold to leave all ſuch private Doctrines to be defended by their own Broachers or Abettors; and ſhall deny, that it will follow, That in caſe of this multitude of Placets, which ſome bold Men have been pleaſed to adopt into the Catalogue of Chriſtian Verities, any or all ſhould be found inconſiſtent with right Reaſon, the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be ſo too. For by that name I underſtand onely that Syſtem of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd Truths that are clearly deliver'd in the Scriptures; or by legitimate and manifeſt conſequences deduc'd thence. And by this one Declaration ſo many unneceſſary and perhaps hurtful Retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Chriſtianity will be at once thrown off, that I doubt not, but if you conſider the Matter aright, you will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcern, that by this firſt Diſtinction I have much leſſen'd the work that is to be done by thoſe that are to follow it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48436:17"/>
                     <head>SECT. II.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In the next place, among the things that ſeem not rational in Religion, I make a great difference between thoſe, in which unenlightned Reaſon is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a competent Judge, and thoſe which Natural Reaſon it ſelf may diſcern to be out of its Sphere.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You will allow me, That Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Theology is ſufficient to evince the Exiſtence of the Deity; and we know that many of the old Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, that were unaſſiſted by Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were, by the force of Reaſon, led to diſcover and confeſs a God, that is, a Being ſupremely perfect; under which Notion divers of them expreſly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him. Now, if there be ſuch a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 'tis but reaſonable to conceive, that there may be many things relating to his Nature, his Will, and his manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things, that are without the <hi>Sphere</hi> of meer or unaſſiſted Reaſon. For, if his Attributes and Perfections be not fully comprehenſible to our Reaſon, we can have but inadequate Conceptions of them; and ſince God
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48436:18"/>is a Being, <hi>toto Caelo,</hi> as they ſpeak, differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from all other Beings, there may be ſome things in his Nature, and in the manner of his Exiſtence, which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Example or perfect Analogy in inferior Beings. For we ſee, that ev'n in Man himſelf the Coexiſtence and intimate Union of the Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that is, an Immaterial and a Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real ſubſtance, is without all Preſident or Parallel in Nature. And though the truth of this Union may be prov'd; yet the manner of it was never yet, nor perhaps ever will be, in this Life clearly underſtood, (to which purpoſe I ſhall elſewhere ſay more.) Moreover, if we ſuppoſe God to be Omnipotent, (that is, to be able to do whatever involves no Contradiction that it ſhould be done,) we muſt allow him to be able to do many things that no other Agent can afford us any Examples of, and ſome of them perhaps ſuch, as we, who are but finite, and are wont to judge of things by Analogy, cannot conceive how they can be perform'd. Of the laſt ſort of things may be the recollect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſufficient quantity of the ſcatter'd matter of a Dead humane Body, and the contriving of it ſo, that (whether alone
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48436:18"/>or with ſome addition of other Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) upon a reconjunction with the Soul, it may again conſtitute a living Man, and ſo effect that Wonder we call the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> Of the latter ſort is the Creation of Matter out of nothing, and much more the like Production of thoſe Rational and Intelligent Beings, <hi>Humane Souls.</hi> For as for <hi>Angels</hi> (good or bad,) I doubt, whether meer Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy can evince their Exiſtence, though I think it may the poſſibility thereof. And ſince we allow the Deity a Wiſdom equal to this boundleſs Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, 'tis but reaſonable to conceive, that theſe unlimited Attributes conſpiring may produce Contrivances and frame Deſigns, which we Men muſt be unable (at leaſt of our ſelves) ſufficiently to underſtand, and to reach to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of. And by this way of arguing it may be made to appear, That there may be many things relating to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity above the reach of unenlightned humane Reaſon. Not that I affirm <hi>all</hi> theſe things to be in their own Nature incomprehenſible to us (though <hi>ſome</hi> of them may be ſo,) when they are once propos'd; but that Reaſon by its own light could not diſcover them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48436:19"/>and therefore it muſt owe its knowledge of them to Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And if God vouchſafes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe thoſe things to us, ſince not only he muſt needs know about his own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Attributes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what we cannot poſſibly know unleſs he tells us, and ſince we know, that whatever he tells us is infallibly true, we have abundant Reaſon to believe rather what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to us concerning Himſelf and Divine things, than what we ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude or gueſs about them by Analogy to things of a nature infinitely diſtant from his, or by Maxims fram'd accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the nature of inferior Beings. If therefore he clearly reveal to us, That there is in the Godhead, Three diſtinct Perſons, and yet that God is One, we, that think our ſelves bound to believe God's Teſtimony in all other Caſes, ought ſure not to disbelieve it concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, but to acknowledge, that in an unparallel'd and incomprehenſible Being, there may be a manner of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence not to be parallel'd in any other Being, though it ſhould never be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by us Men, who cannot clearly comprehend, how in our ſelves two ſuch diſtant Natures as that of a groſs Body
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48436:19"/>and an immaterial Spirit, ſhould be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo as to make up one Man. In ſuch caſes therefore as we are now ſpeaking of, there muſt indeed be ſomething that looks like captivating ones Reaſon, but 'tis a ſubmiſſion that Reaſon it ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to make; and he that in ſuch points as theſe believes rather what the Divine Writings teach him, than what he would think if they had never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd him, does not renounce or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave his Reaſon, but ſuffers it to be Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil to an Omniſcient and Infallible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer, who can teach him ſuch things, as neither his own meer Reaſon, nor any others could ever have diſcovered to him.</p>
                     <p>I thought to have here diſmiſs'd this Propoſition, but I muſt not omit to give it a confirmation afforded me by chance (or rather Providence:) For, ſince I writ the laſt Paragraph, reſuming a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Enquiry, I met in proſecuting it with a couple of Teſtimonies of the truth of what I was lately telling you, which are given not by Divines or Schoolmen, but by a couple of famous Mathematicians, that have both led the way to many of the Modern Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers to ſhake off the reverence wont
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48436:20"/>to be born to the Authority of great Names, and have advanc'd Reaſon in a few years more than ſuch as <hi>Vaninus</hi> and <hi>Pomponatius</hi> would do in many Ages; and have always boldly, and ſometimes ſucceſsfully attempted to explain intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligibly thoſe things, which others ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled not either openly or tacitly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs inexplicable.</p>
                     <p>The firſt of theſe Teſtimonies I met with in a little <hi>French</hi> Treatiſe put out by ſome Mathematician, who, though he conceals his Name, appears by his way of writing to be a great <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> and takes upon him to give his Readers in <hi>French</hi> the new thoughts of <hi>Galilaeo,</hi> by making that the Title of his Book. This Writer then ſpeaking of a Paradox (which I but recite) of <hi>Galilaeo's,</hi> that makes a point equal to a Circle, adds, <hi>Et per conſequent l'on peut dire,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pag. 22, 23.</note> 
                        <hi>i. e.</hi> and conſequently one may ſay, that all Circles are equal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves, ſince each of them is equal to a point. For though the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination be overpower'd by this Idea or Notion; yet Reaſon will ſuffer it ſelf to be perſuaded of it. I know <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues he)</hi> divers other excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (beſides <hi>Galilaeo</hi>) who conclude
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48436:20"/>the ſame thing by other ways, but all are conſtrain'd to acknowledge, that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſible</hi> and <hi>infinite</hi> are things that do ſo ſwallow up the mind of Man, that he ſcarce knows what to pitch on, when he contemplates them. For it will follow from <hi>Galilaeo</hi>'s Speculation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which paſſage I have cited, to ſhew you, that <hi>Galilaeo</hi> is not the only Philoſopher and Mathematician who has confeſs'd his Reaſon quite paſſed about the Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of what is Infinite.</p>
                     <p>The other Teſtimony I mention'd to you, is that of the excellent <hi>Deſ-Cartes</hi> in the ſecond Part of his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Philoſophy,
<note place="margin">Numb. 34.</note> where ſpeaking of the Circle to be made by Matter moving through places ſtill leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and leſſer, he has this ingenious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment; <hi>Fatendum tamen eſt</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>in motu iſto aliquid reperiri, quod mens quidem noſtra pereipit eſſe verum, ſed tamen quo pacto fiat non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendit, nempe Diviſionem quarundam particularum Materiae in infinitum, ſive indefinitam, atque in tot partes ut nulla cogitatione determinare poſſimus tam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iguam, quin intelligamus ipſam in alias adhuc minores reipſa eſſe diviſam.</hi> And in the Cloſe of the next Paragraph, he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48436:21"/>gives this for a Reaſon, why, though we cannot comprehend this indefinite di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, yet we ought not to doubt of the truth of it, That we diſcern it to be of that kind of things that cannot be compriz'd by our minds as being but finite.</p>
                     <p>If then ſuch bold and piercing Wits, and ſuch excellent Mathematicians are forc'd to confeſs, that not only their own Reaſon, but that of Mankind may be paſſed and non-plus'd about <hi>Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which is an Object of contemplation Natural, nay, Mathematical, and which is the Subject of the rigid Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of pure Mathematicks; why ſhould we think it unfit to be believ'd, and to be acknowledg'd, that in the Attributes of God, who is eſſentially an Infinite Being, and an <hi>Ens ſingulariſſimum,</hi> and in divers other Divine things, of which we can have no knowledge without Revelation, there ſhould be ſome things, that our Finite underſtandings cannot, eſpecially in this life, clearly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48436:21"/>
                     <head>SECT. III.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To this Conſideration, I ſhall for Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities ſake ſubjoin another, which I leave to your Liberty to look upon as a diſtinct one, or as an Enlargement and Application of the former.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I conſider then, that there is a great difference between a Doctrines being repugnant to the general and well-weigh'd Rules or Dictates of Reaſon, in the forming of which Rules it may be ſuppos'd to have been duly conſider'd; and its diſagreeing with Axioms, at the Eſtabliſhment whereof the Doctrine in Queſtion was probably never thought on. There are ſeveral Rules that paſs current ev'n among the moſt Learned Men, and which are indeed of very great uſe when reſtrain'd to thoſe things whence they took their Riſe, and others of the like nature; which yet ought not to overthrow thoſe Divine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines that ſeem not conſonant to them. For the Framers of theſe Rules having generally built them upon the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations they had made of Natural and Moral things, ſince (as we lately argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48436:22"/>Reaſon it ſelf cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, there are ſome things out of its Sphere, we muſt not think it impoſſible, that there may be Rules, which will hold in all inferior Beings for which they were made; and yet not reach to that infinite and moſt ſingular Being call'd God, and to ſome Divine matters which were not taken into Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on when thoſe Rules were fram'd. And indeed, if we conſider God as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Univerſe, and the free Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſher of the Laws of Motion, whoſe general Concourſe is neceſſary to the Conſervation and Efficacy of every particular Phyſical Agent, we cannot but acknowledge, that by with-holding his Concourſe or changing theſe Laws of Motion, which depend perfectly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Will, he may invalidate moſt, if not all, the Axioms and Theorems of Natural Philoſophy: Theſe ſuppoſing the Courſe of Nature, and eſpecially the Eſtabliſh'd Laws of Motion among the parts of the Univerſal Matter, as thoſe upon which all the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture depend. 'Tis a Rule in Natural Philoſophy, that <hi>Cauſae neceſſariae ſemper agunt quantum poſſunt;</hi> But it will not follow from thence, that the Fire muſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48436:22"/>neceſſarily burn <hi>Daniel</hi>'s three Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions or their Cloaths, that were caſt by the <hi>Babylonian</hi> King's Command into the midſt of a Burning fiery Furnace, when the Author of Nature was pleas'd to withdraw his Concourſe to the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the flames, or ſupernaturally to defend againſt them the Bodies that were expoſed to them. That Men once truly dead cannot be brought to life again, hath been in all Ages the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of meer Philoſophers; but though this be true according to the Courſe of Nature, yet it will not follow but that the contrary may be true, if God inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe either to recall the departed Soul and reconjoin it to the Body, if the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganization of this be not too much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated, or by ſo altering the Fabrick of the matter whereof the Carkaſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, as to reſtore it to a fitneſs for the Exerciſe of the Functions of Life. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greably to this let me obſerve to you, that, though it be unreaſonable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Miraculous Effect when attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely to a meer Phyſical Agent; yet the ſame thing may reaſonably be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, when aſcrib'd to God, or to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents aſſiſted with his abſolute or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Power. That a Man born
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48436:23"/>blind ſhould in a trice recover his ſight upon the Application of Clay and Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, would juſtly appear incredible, if the Cure were aſcrib'd to one that act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a meer Man; but it will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that it ought to be incredible, that the Son of God ſhould work it. And the like may be ſaid of all the Miracles perform'd by Chriſt, and thoſe Apoſtles and other Diſciples of his, that acted by virtue of a Divine Power and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. For in all theſe and the like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it ſuffices not to make ones Belief ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational, that the things believ'd are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be true according to the courſe of Nature; but it muſt be ſhewn, either that they are impoſſible even to the Power of God to which they are aſcrib'd, or that the Records, we have of them, are not ſufficient to beget Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in the nature of a Teſtimony; which latter Objection againſt theſe Relations is Forreign to our preſent Diſcourſe. And as the Rules about the power of Agents will not all of them hold in God; ſo I might ſhew the like, if I had time, concerning ſome of his other At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes: Inſomuch that ev'n in point of Juſtice, wherein we think we may free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt make Eſtimates of what may or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48436:23"/>may not be done, there may be <hi>ſome</hi> caſes, wherein God's ſupreme Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Maker and Governor of the World, places him above <hi>ſome</hi> of thoſe Rules; I ſay, <hi>ſome,</hi> for I ſay not above <hi>all</hi> thoſe Rules of Juſtice which oblige all inferior Beings, without excepting the greateſt and moſt abſolute Monarchs themſelves. I will not give Examples of his Power of Pardoning or Remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Penalties, which is but a relaxing of his own Right; but will rather give an inſtance in his Power of afflicting and exterminating Men, without any Provocation given him by them. I will not here enter upon the Controverſie <hi>de Jure Dei in Creaturas,</hi> upon what it is founded, and how far it reaches. For, without making my ſelf a party in that Quarrel, I think, I may ſafely ſay, that God by his right of Dominion, might, without any violation of the Laws of Juſtice, have deſtroy'd and ev'n annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> before they had eaten of the forbidden Fruit, or had been commanded to abſtain from it. For Man being as much and as intirely God's Workmanſhip as any of the other Creatures; unleſs God had oblig'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by ſome promiſe or pact to limit the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48436:24"/>Exerciſe of his abſolute dominion over him, God was no more bound to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> long alive, than he was to preſerve a Lamb, or a Pigeon; and therefore, as we allow, that he might juſtly recall the Lives he had giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en thoſe innocent Creatures when he pleas'd, (as actually he often order'd them to be kill'd and burn'd in Sacrifice to him:) ſo he might, for the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Power to the Angels, or for other Reaſons, have ſuddenly taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Lives of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> though they had never offended him. And upon the ſame grounds he might without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice have annihilated, I ſay not, damn'd their Souls; he being no more bound to continue Exiſtence to a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, than a leſs noble Creature: As he is no more bound to keep an <hi>Eagle</hi> than an <hi>Oyſter</hi> always alive. I know, there is a difference betwixt Gods reſuming a Being he lent <hi>Adam,</hi> and his doing the ſame to inferior Creatures: But that diſparity if it concern any of his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, will concern ſome other than his Juſtice; which allow'd him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume at pleaſure the Being he had only lent them, or lay any Affliction on them that were leſſer than that Good could
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48436:24"/>countervail. But mentioning this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance only occaſionally, I ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it any further, but rather mind you of the Reſult of this and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Conſideration; which is, That Divinely reveal'd Truths may <hi>ſeem</hi> to be repugnant to the dictates of Reaſon, when they do <hi>but ſeem</hi> to be ſo: Nor does Chriſtianity oblige us to queſtion ſuch Rules as to the caſes they were fram'd for, but the application of them <hi>to</hi> the Nature of God, who has already been truly ſaid to be <hi>Ens ſingulariſſimum,</hi> and <hi>to</hi> his abſolute Power and Will; ſo that we do not reject the Rules we ſpeak of, but rather limit them; and when we have reſtrain'd them to their due bounds, we may ſafely admit them.</p>
                     <p>From Mens not taking notice of, or not pondering this neceſſary limitation of many Axioms deliver'd in general terms, ſeems to have proceeded a great Error, which has made ſo many Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men preſume to ſay, That this or that thing is true in Philoſophy, but falſe in Divinity, or on the contrary: As for inſtance, that a Virgin, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch, may have a Child, is look'd upon as an Article which Theology aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48436:25"/>to be true, and Philoſophy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces impoſſible. But the Objection is grounded upon a miſtake, which might have been prevented by wording the Propoſitions more warily and fully. For though we grant, that, Phyſically ſpeaking, 'tis falſe, that a Virgin can bring forth a Child; yet that ſignifies no more, than that, according to the courſe of Nature, ſuch a thing cannot come to paſs; but ſpeaking abſolutely and indefinitely, without confining the Effect to meer Phyſical Agents, it may ſafely be deny'd that Philoſophy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces it impoſſible that a Virgin ſhould be a Mother. For why ſhould the Author of Nature be confin'd to the ways of working of dependent and finite Agents? And to apply the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Divines that hold the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I oppoſe; I ſhall demand, why God may not out of the ſubſtance of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man form a Man, without the help of a Man, as well as at the beginning of the ſubſtance of a Man he form'd a Woman without the concurrence of a Woman? And ſo, that <hi>Iron</hi> being a Body far hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier, (<hi>in ſpecie,</hi> as they ſpeak,) will, if upheld by no other Body, ſink in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is a Truth in Natural Philoſophy;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48436:25"/>but ſince Phyſicks themſelves lead Men to the acknowledgment of a God, 'tis not repugnant to Reaſon, that, if God pleaſe to interpoſe his Power, he may (as in <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s caſe) make <hi>Iron</hi> ſwim, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by withholding his concourſe to the Agents, whatever they be that cauſe Gravity in Bodies, or perhaps by other ways unknown to us; ſince a vigorous Loadſtone may, as I have more than once try'd, keep a piece of Iron, which it touches not, ſwimming in the Air, though this thin Body muſt contribute far leſs, than water would, to the ſuſtaining it aloft.</p>
                     <p>That ſtrict Philoſopher <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> who has with great Wit and no leſs Applauſe attempted to carry the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanical Powers of matters higher than any of the Modern Philoſophers; this Naturaliſt, I ſay, that aſcribes ſo great a power to <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion,</hi> was ſo far from thinking, that what was impoſſible to them, muſt be ſo to God too, that, though he were urg'd by a learned Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary with an Argument as likely as any to give him a ſtrong Temptation to limit the Omnipotence of God; yet ev'n on this occaſion he ſcruples not to make this ingenious and wary Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48436:26"/>and that in a private Letter; <hi>For my part,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I think we ought never to ſay of any thing that 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to God. For all that is true and good being dependent on his Almightineſs, I dare not ſo much as ſay, that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make a Mountain without a Valley, or cannot make it true,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Volum. ſecond Lettre vi.</note> 
                        <hi>that one and two ſhall not make three; but I ſay only, that he has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me a Soul of ſuch a nature, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive a Mountain without a Valley, nor that the Aggregate of one and of two ſhall not make three,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and I ſay only, that ſuch things imply a Contradiction in my Conception.</hi> And conſonantly to this in his Principles of Philoſophy he gives on a certain occaſion this uſeful Caution,—<hi>Quod ut ſatis tutò &amp; ſine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi periculo aggrediamur,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Parte prima. Artic. 24.</note> 
                        <hi>eâ nobis cautelâ eſt utendum, ut ſemper quàm maxime re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordemur, &amp; Deum Autorem rerum eſſe infinitum, &amp; Nos omnina finitos.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48436:26"/>
                     <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In the next place, I think we ought to diſtinguiſh between Reaſon conſider'd in it ſelf, and Reaſon conſider'd in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it, by this or that Philoſopher, or by this or that Man, or by this or that Company or Society of Men, whether all of one Sect, or of more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If you will allow me to borrow a School-phraſe, I ſhall expreſs this more ſhortly by ſaying, I diſtinguiſh between Reaſon <hi>in Abſtracto,</hi> and <hi>in Concreto.</hi> To clear this matter, we may conſider, That whatever you make the Faculty of Reaſon to be in it ſelf, yet the Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocinations it produces are made by Men, either ſingly reaſoning, or concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the ſame Ratiocinations and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions; and conſequently, if theſe Men do not make the beſt uſe of their Reaſoning Faculty, it will not be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that what thwarts <hi>their</hi> Ratiocina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, muſt likewiſe thwart the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or the Dictates of <hi>right Reaſon.</hi> For, Man having a Will and Affections as well as an Intellect, though our Dijudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and Tenents ought indeed (in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48436:27"/>matters ſpeculative) to be made and pitch'd upon by our unbiaſs'd Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings; yet really our Intellectual Weakneſſes, or our Prejudices, or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſion by Cuſtom, Education, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> our Intereſt, Paſſions, Vices, and I know not how many other things, have ſo great and ſwaying an Influence on them, that there are very few Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that we make, or Opinions that we eſpouſe, that are ſo much the pure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults of our Reaſon, that no perſonal Diſability, Prejudice, or Fault, has any Intereſt in them.</p>
                     <p>This I have elſewhere more amply diſcours'd of on another occaſion;
<note place="margin">About the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall now add but this, That the diſtinction, I have been propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, does (if I miſtake not) reach a great deal further than you may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of. For not only whole Sects, whether in Religion or Philoſophy, are in many caſes ſubject to Prepoſſeſſions, Envy, Ambition, Intereſt, and other misleading things, as well as ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but, which is more conſiderable to our preſent purpoſe, the very Body of Mankind may be embued with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices, and Errors, and that from their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48436:27"/>Childhood, and ſome alſo ev'n from their Birth, by which means they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue undiſcern'd and conſequently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reform'd.</p>
                     <p>This you will think an Accuſation as bold as high; but to let you ſee, that the Philoſophers, you moſt reſpect, have made the ſame Obſervation, though not apply'd to the ſame caſe, I muſt put you in mind, that Monſieur <hi>Des Cartes</hi> begins his Principles of Philoſophy with taking notice, That, becauſe we are born Children, we make divers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Judgments of things, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards are wont to continue with us all our Lives, and prove radicated Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that miſlead our Judgments on ſo many occaſions, that he elſewhere tells us, he found no other way to ſecure himſelf from their Influence, but once in his Life ſolemnly to doubt of the Truth of all that he had till then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, in order to the re-examining of his former Dijudications. But I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, our illuſtrious <hi>Verulam</hi> warrants a yet further Prejudice againſt many things that are wont to be look'd on as the ſuggeſtions of Reaſon. For having told us, That the Mind of Man is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd with four differing kinds of Idols
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48436:28"/>or Phantaſms, when he comes to enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them, he teaches, that there are not only ſuch as Men get by Converſation and Diſcourſe one with another, and ſuch as proceed from the divers <hi>Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> or <hi>Theories</hi> and <hi>Opinions</hi> of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, and from the perverſe ways of Demonſtration, and likewiſe ſuch as are perſonal to this or that Man, proceeding from his Education, Temperament, Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſuch as he calls <hi>Idola tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> becauſe they are founded in humane Nature it ſelf, and in the very Tribe or Nation of Mankind; and of theſe he particularly diſcourſes of ſeven or eight; As that the Intellect of Man has an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Propenſity to ſuppoſe in things a greater order and equality than it finds, and that being unable to reſt or acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce, it does alwayes tend further and further; to which he adds divers other innate prejudices of Mankind, which he ſollicitouſly as well as judiciouſly endeavors to remove.</p>
                     <p>Now, if not only ſingle Philoſophers, and particular Sects, but the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Mankind be ſubject to be ſway'd by innate and unheeded Prejudices and Proclivities to Errors about matters that are neither Divine, nor Moral, nor
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48436:28"/>Political, but Phyſical, where the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of Truth is exceeding plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to humane Nature, and is not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with conſequences diſtaſteful to it: Why may not we juſtly ſuſpect not only this or that Philoſopher or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sect; but the generality of Men, of having ſome ſecret propenſities to err about Divine things, and indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to admit Truths, which not only detect the weakneſſes of our Nature, and our perſonal diſabilities, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by offend or mortifie our Pride and our Ambition, but ſhine into the Mind with ſo clear as well as pure and chaſte a light, as is proper both to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to our ſelves and others our Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Faults, and oftentimes to croſs our Deſigns and Intereſts?</p>
                     <p>And to this purpoſe we may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that divers of thoſe very Idols, which my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> obſerves to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege or pervert Mens Judgments in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to things <hi>Natural,</hi> may probably have the ſame kind of influence (and that much ſtronger) on the minds of Men in reference to <hi>Supernatural</hi> things. Thus he takes notice, that, if ſome things have once pleas'd the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, 'tis apt to draw all others to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48436:29"/>comport with, and give Suffrage, to them, though perhaps the Inducements to the contrary belief be either more numerous or more weighty. He ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves alſo, that Man is apt to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſenſes and other perceptions as the meaſures of things, and alſo, that the underſtanding of Man is not ſincerely diſpos'd to receive the light of Truth, but receives an infuſion as it were of adventitious Colours (that diſguiſe the light) from the Will and Affections, which makes him ſooner believe thoſe things that he is deſirous ſhould be true, and reject many others upon Accounts that do no way infer their being falſe. Now if we apply theſe things to Divine Truths (to which 'twere well they were leſs juſtly applicable) and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that in our Youth we generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe but with things Corporeal, and are ſway'd by Affections that have them for their Objects, we ſhall not much wonder, that Men ſhould be very prone, <hi>either</hi> to frame ſuch Notions of Divine things as they were wont to have about others of a far different and meaner na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>or</hi> elſe to reject them for not being Analogous to thoſe things which they have been us'd to employ for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48436:29"/>of truth and falſity. And if we conſider the inbred pride of man, which is ſuch, that if we will believe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſtory, ev'n <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be like God knowing good and evil, we ſhall not ſo much marvel, that almoſt every man in particular makes the Notions he has entertain'd already, and his Senſes, his Inclinations and his Intereſts, the Standards by which he eſtimates and judges of all other things, whether natural or reveal'd. And as <hi>Heraclitus</hi> juſtly complain'd, that every man ſought the knowledge of natural things in the <hi>Microcoſm,</hi> that is, himſelf, and not in the <hi>Macrocoſm,</hi> the World; ſo we may juſtly complain, that men ſeek all the knowledge, they care to find, or will admit, either in theſe little worlds themſelves, or from that great World, the Univerſe; but not from the Omniſcient Author of them both. And laſtly, if ev'n in purely Phyſical things, where one would not think it likely, that rational Beings ſhould ſeek Truth with any other deſigns than of finding and enjoying it, our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are ſo univerſally byaſs'd, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon by our Wills and Affections; how can we admire, eſpecially if we
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48436:30"/>admit the fall of our firſt Parents, that our Paſſions and Intereſts, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our Vices ſhould pervert our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellects about thoſe reveal'd Truths; divers of which we diſcern to be above our comprehenſions, and more of which we find to be directly contrary to our Inclinations,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. V.</head>
                     <p>And now 'twill be ſeaſonable for me to tell you, That I think, there may be a great difference betwixt a things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to <hi>right Reaſon,</hi> or ſo much as to any <hi>true Philoſophy,</hi> and its being contrary to the <hi>receiv'd Opinions</hi> of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, or to the Principles or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of <hi>this or that Sect</hi> of them.</p>
                     <p>For here I may juſtly apply to my preſent purpoſe, what <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus</hi> judiciouſly ſaid on another Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, that Philoſophy was neither Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripatetical, nor Stoical, nor Epicurean, but whatſoever among all thoſe ſeveral parties was fit to be approv'd.</p>
                     <p>And indeed if we ſurvey the <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſes</hi> and Opinions of the ſeveral Sects of Philoſophers, eſpecially in thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48436:30"/>points wherein they hold things repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Theological Truths, we ſhall find many of them ſo ſlightly grounded, and ſo diſagreeing among themſelves, that a ſevere and inquiſitive Examiner would ſee little cauſe to admit them upon the bare Account of his being a Philoſopher, though he did not ſee any to reject them upon the Account of his being a Chriſtian. And in particular, as to the <hi>Peripateticks,</hi> who by invading all the Schools of <hi>Europe</hi> (and ſome in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africk</hi>) have made their Sect almoſt Catholick, and have produc'd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the famous Queſtioners of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in the laſt Age, and the firſt part of this; the World begins to be apace undeceiv'd as to many of their Doctrines, which were as confidently taught and believ'd for many Ages, as thoſe that are repugnant to our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and there is now ſcarce any of the modern Philoſophers that allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the free uſe of their Reaſon, who believes any longer, <hi>that</hi> there is an Element of Fire lodg'd under the ſuppos'd Sphere of the Moon; <hi>that</hi> Heaven conſiſts of ſolid Orbs; <hi>that</hi> all Celeſtial Bodies are ingenerable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible; <hi>that</hi> the Heart, rather than
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48436:31"/>the Brain, is the Origine of Nerves; <hi>that</hi> the torrid Zone is uninhabitable; and I know not how many other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the <hi>Ariſtotelians,</hi> which our <hi>Corpuſcularian</hi> Philoſophers think ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle worth being believ'd, that they would cenſure him, that ſhould now think them worthy to be ſollicitouſly confuted; upon which ſcore, I preſume you will allow me to leave thoſe and divers others as weak Peripatetick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, to fall by their own groundleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                     <p>But you will tell me, that the <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans,</hi> and the <hi>Somatici,</hi> that will allow nothing but Body in the World, nor no Author of it but Chance, are more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Enemies to Religion than the <hi>Ariſtotelians.</hi> And indeed I am apt to think they are ſo, but they may well be ſo without deſerving to have any of their Sects look'd upon as Philoſophy it ſelf, there being none of them that I know of, that maintain any Opinion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Chriſtianity, that I think may not be made appear to be alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to Reaſon, or at leaſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable by it. You will not expect I ſhould deſcend to particulars, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally having expreſly diſcours'd againſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48436:31"/>the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Hypotheſis of the Origine of the World in another Paper; and therefore I ſhall obſerve to you in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that the <hi>Carteſian</hi> Philoſophers, who lay aſide all Supernatural Revelation in their Inquiries into Natural things, do yet both think, and, as to the two firſt of them, very plauſibly prove, the three grand Principles of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> That the little Bodies he calls Atoms are indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, That they all have their motion from themſelves, and That there is a <hi>vacuum</hi> in <hi>rerum naturâ,</hi> to be as repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to meer Reaſon, as the <hi>Epicureans</hi> think the Notion of an Incorporeal Subſtance, or the Creation of the World, or the Immortality of the Soul. And as for the new <hi>Somatici,</hi> ſuch as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> (and ſome few others) by what I have yet ſeen of his, I am not much tempted to forſake any thing that I look'd upon as a Truth before, ev'n in Natural Philoſophy it ſelf, upon the ſcore of what he (though never ſo confidently) delivers, by which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I ſee not, that he hath made any great diſcovery either of new Truths, or old Errors. An Honourable Member of the Royal Society, hath elſewhere pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſhewn, how ill he has prov'd his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48436:32"/>own Opinions about the Air, and ſome other Phyſical Subjects, and how ill he has underſtood and oppos'd thoſe of his Adverſary. But to give you in this place a <hi>Specimen</hi> how little their repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy to his Principles or Natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, ought to affright us from thoſe Theological Doctrines they contradict, I ſhall here (but not in the Body of this Diſcourſe, for fear of too much inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting it) examine the fundamental Maxim of his whole Phyſicks, <hi>That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is removed but by a Body contiguous and moved;</hi> it having been already ſhewn (by the Gentleman newly mention'd) that, as to the next to it, which is, <hi>that there is no vacuum,</hi> whether it be <hi>true</hi> or no, <hi>he</hi> has not <hi>prov'd</hi> it.</p>
                     <p>If no Body can poſſibly be moved but by a Body contiguous and moved, as Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> teaches; I demand, How there comes to be Local motion in the World? For, <hi>either</hi> all the portions of matter that compos'd the Univerſe, have motion belonging to their Nature, which the <hi>Epicureans</hi> affirm'd for their Atoms; <hi>or</hi> ſome parts of Matter have this motive power, and ſome have not; or elſe none of them have it, but all of them are naturally devoid of Motion.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48436:32"/>If it be granted, that Motion does na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally belong to all parts of Matter, the diſpute is at an end, the conceſſion quite overthrowing the <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> If it be ſaid, that naturally ſome portions of Matter have Motion, and others not, then the Aſſertion will not be Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally true: For though it may hold in the parts that are naturally moveleſs or quieſcent, yet it will not do ſo in the others, there being nothing that may ſhew a neceſſity, why a Body, to which Motion is natural, ſhould not be capable of moving without being put into mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by another contiguous and moved. And if there be no Body to which Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is natural, but every Body needs an outward movent, it may well be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, How there comes to be any thing Locally mov'd in the World; which yet conſtant and obvious experience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates, and Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> himſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny. For if no part of Matter have any Motion but what it muſt owe to another that is contiguous to it, and being it ſelf in Motion impels it; and if there be nothing but <hi>Matter</hi> in the World, how can there come to be any Motion amongſt Bodies, ſince they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have it upon the ſcore of their own
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48436:33"/>nature, nor can receive it from external Agents. If Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> ſhould reply, that the Motion is impreſs'd upon any of the parts of the Matter by <hi>God,</hi> he will ſay that which I moſt readily grant to be true, but will not ſerve <hi>his</hi> turn, if he would ſpeak congruouſly to his own <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> For I demand, Whether this Supreme Being, that the Aſſertion has recourſe to, be a Corporeal or an Incorporeal Subſtance? If it be the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet be the efficient Cauſe of Motion in Bodies, then it will not be Univerſally true, that whatſoever Body is moved, is ſo by a <hi>Body</hi> contiguous and moved. For, in our ſuppoſition, the Bodies that God moves either immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, or by the intervention of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Immaterial Being, are not moved by a <hi>Body</hi> contiguous, but by an <hi>Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real</hi> Spirit. But becauſe Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> in ſome Writings of his, is believed to think the very Notion of an Immaterial Subſtance to be abſurd, and to involve a Contradiction, and becauſe it may be ſubſum'd, that if God be not an Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Subſtance, he muſt by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence be a Material and Corporeal one, there being no <hi>Medium Negationis,</hi> or third Subſtance that is none of thoſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48436:33"/>two: I anſwer, That, if this be ſaid, and ſo that Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Deity be a Corporeal one, the ſame difficulty will recurr, that I urg'd before. For this Body will not, by Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s calling or thinking it <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> ceaſe to be a true Body, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently a portion of <hi>Divine</hi> Matter will not be able to move a portion of our <hi>Mundane</hi> Matter without it be it ſelf contiguous and moved; which it cannot be but by another portion of Divine Matter ſo qualified to impreſs a Motion, nor this again but by another portion.</p>
                     <p>And beſides, that it will breed a ſtrange confuſion in rendring the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Cauſes of things, unleſs an expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent be found to teach us how to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh accurately the <hi>Mundane</hi> Bodies from the <hi>Divine</hi> (which will perhaps prove no eaſie task;) I ſee not yet, how this <hi>Corporeal Deity</hi> will make good the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> I examine. For I demand, How this <hi>Divine Matter</hi> comes to have this Local Motion that is aſcrib'd to it? If it be anſwer'd, That it hath it from its own Nature, without any other Cauſe; ſince the <hi>Epicureans</hi> affirm the ſame of their Atoms, or meerly <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane</hi> Matter, I demand, How the Truth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48436:34"/>of Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Opinion will appear to me, to whom it ſeems as likely by the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of Nature that occur, that <hi>Mundane</hi> Matter ſhould have a congenit Motion, as that any thing that is Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal can be <hi>God,</hi> and capable of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it; which to be, it muſt, for ought we know, have its Subſiſtence divided into as many minute parts, as there are Corpuſcles and Particles in the World that move ſeparately from their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring ones. And, to draw towards a Concluſion, I ſay, that theſe minute <hi>Divine</hi> Bodies, that thus moved thoſe portions of <hi>Mundane</hi> Matter, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> denies that they can be moved but by Bodies contiguous and moved, theſe Divine Subſtances, I ſay, are, according to the late ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, true Bodies, and yet are moved themſelves not by Bodies contiguous and moved, but by a Motion which muſt be <hi>Innate,</hi> deriv'd or flowing from their very eſſence or nature, ſince no ſuch Body is pretended to have a Being as cannot be refer'd as a portion, either to the <hi>Mundane,</hi> or the <hi>Divine</hi> Matter. In ſhort, ſince Local Motion is to be found in one, if not in both, of theſe two Matters, it muſt be natural to (at leaſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48436:34"/>ſome parts of) one of them in Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Hypotheſis; for, though he ſhould grant an <hi>Immaterial</hi> Being, yet it could not produce a Motion in any Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſince, according to him, no Body can be moved but by another <hi>Body</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiguous and mov'd.</p>
                     <p>As then to this grand Poſition of Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> though, if it were cautiouſly propos'd as it is by <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> it may perhaps be ſafely admitted, becauſe <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſius</hi> acknowledges, the firſt Impulſe that ſet Matter a moving, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Motion once begun, to come from God; yet, as 'tis crudely propos'd by the favourers of Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> I am ſo far from ſeeing any ſuch cogent Proof for it, (as were to be wiſh'd for a Principle on which he builds ſo much, and which yet is not at all evident by its own light,) that I ſee no competent Reaſon to admit it.</p>
                     <p>I expect your Friend ſhould here op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to what I have been ſaying, that formerly recited Sentence, that is ſo commonly employ'd in the Schools as well of Divines as of Philoſophers: That ſuch or ſuch an Opinion is true in Divinity, but falſe in Philoſophy; or on the contrary, Philoſophically true, but Theologically falſe.</p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:48436:35"/>
                     <p>Upon what Warrant thoſe, that are wont to employ ſuch Expreſſions, ground their Practice, I leave to them to make out; but as to the Objection it ſelf, as it ſuppoſes theſe ways of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be well grounded, give me leave to conſider, That <hi>Philoſophy</hi> may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie two things, which I take to be very differing.</p>
                     <p>For <hi>firſt</hi> 'tis moſt commonly employ'd to ſignifie a Syſtem or Body of the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and other Doctrines of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sect of thoſe Philoſophers that make uſe of the Word. As when an <hi>Ariſtotelian</hi> talks of Philoſophy, he uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally means the <hi>Peripatetick,</hi> as an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean</hi> do's the <hi>Atomical,</hi> or a <hi>Platoniſt</hi> the <hi>Platonick.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But we may alſo in a more general and no leſs juſt Acception of the term, underſtand by Philoſophy, a Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of all thoſe Truths or Doctrines, which the natural Reaſon of man, freed from Prejudices and Partiality, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by Learning, Attention, Exerciſe, Experiments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> can manifeſtly make out, or by neceſſary conſequence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce from clear and certain Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:48436:35"/>
                     <p>This being briefly premis'd, I muſt in the next place put you in mind of what I formerly obſerv'd to you, that many Opinions are maintain'd by this or that Sect of Chriſtians, or perhaps by the Divinity-Schools of more than one or two Sects, which either do not at all belong to the Chriſtian Religion, or at leaſt ought not to be look'd upon as parts of it, but upon ſuppoſition, that the Philoſophical Principles and Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinations, upon which, and not upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs or meer Revelation, they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd to be founded, are agreable to right Reaſon.</p>
                     <p>And having premis'd theſe two things, I now anſwer more directly to the Objection; that, if Philoſophy be taken in the firſt ſenſe above-mention'd, its teaching things repugnant to Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, eſpecially taking this word in the more large and vulgar ſenſe of it, will not cogently conclude any thing againſt the Chriſtian Religion. But, if Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy be taken in the latter ſenſe for true Philoſophy, and Divinity only for a Syſtem of thoſe Articles that are clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reveal'd as Truths in the Scriptures; I ſhall not allow any thing to be falſe in Philoſophy ſo underſtood that is true in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48436:36"/>Divinity ſo explain'd, till I ſee ſome clearer Proof of it than I have yet met with. I have had occaſion in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Diſcourſe, to ſay ſomething, that may be apply'd to the Point under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; and in the following part of this Letter I ſhall have Occaſion to touch upon it again: And therefore I ſhall now ſay but this in ſhort, That 'tis not likely, that God, being the Author of Reaſon as well as Revelation, ſhould make it mens Duty to believe as true that which there is juſt Reaſon to reject as falſe.</p>
                     <p>There is indeed a Senſe, wherein the Phraſes, I diſapprove, may be tolerated. For if by ſaying, that ſuch a thing is true in Divinity, but falſe in Philoſophy, it were meant, that if the Doctrine were propos'd to a meer Philoſopher, to be judg'd of according to the Principles of his Sect, or at moſt according to what he, being ſuppos'd not to have heard of the Chriſtian Religion, or had it duly propos'd to him, would reject it, the Phraſe might be allow'd, or at leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd. But then we muſt conſider, that the Reaſon why ſuch a Philoſopher would reject the Articles of Chriſtian Faith, would not be, becauſe they could
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48436:36"/>by no <hi>Mediums</hi> be poſſibly prov'd, but becauſe theſe Doctrines being founded upon a Revelation, which he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd either not to have heard of, or not to have had ſufficiently propos'd to him, he muſt, as a Rational man, refuſe to believe them upon the ſcore of their Proofleſneſs. And the ſame Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, ſuppoſing him to be a true one, though he will be very wary, how he admits any thing as true that is not prov'd, if it fall properly under the cognizance of Philoſophy; yet he will be as wary, how he pronounces things to be falſe or impoſſible in matters which he diſcerns to be beyond the reach of meer natural Reaſon, eſpecially if So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Learned men do very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently pretend to know ſomething of thoſe matters by Divine Revelation, which though he will not eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be a true one, yet he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, in caſe it ſhould be prov'd true, to be a fit <hi>Medium</hi> to evince Truths, which, upon the Account of meer natural Light, he could not diſcover or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace. To be ſhort, ſuch a Philoſopher would indeed reject ſome of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our Faith hypothetically; <hi>i. e.</hi>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:48436:37"/>upon ſuppoſition that he need employ no other Touchſtone to examine them by, than the Principles and Dictates of <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> that he is acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with (upon which ſcore I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhew, that divers ſtrange Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Experiments, and other Diſcoveries would alſo be rejected;) but yet he would nor pronounce them falſe, but upon ſuppoſition that the Arguments, by which they lay claim to <hi>Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> are incompetent in their kind. For as he will not eaſily believe any thing within the Sphere of Nature that agrees not with the Eſtabliſh'd Laws of it; ſo he will not eaſily adventure to pronounce one way or other in matters that are <hi>beyond</hi> the Sphere of Nature: He will indeed (as he juſtly may,) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect as full a Proof of the Divine Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony that is pretended, as the Nature of the thing requires and allows; but he will not be backward to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that God to whom that Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is aſcrib'd, is able to know and to do many more things than we can expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>How He</hi> can diſcover, or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine How any <hi>Phyſical Agent</hi> can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:48436:37"/>
                     <p>[Since I propos'd to you this fifth Conſideration, I happen'd to light on a paſſage in <hi>Des Cartes</hi>'s Principles, which affords of what I have been diſcovering the Suffrage of a Philoſopher,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Princip. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſ. part. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Artic.</hi> 25.</note> that is wont to be accus'd of excluding Theology too ſcrupulouſly out of his Philoſophy. His words are ſo full to my preſent Purpoſe, that I need not, to accommodate them to it, alter one of them, and therefore ſhall tranſcribe them juſt as they lie: <hi>Si fortè nobis De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de ſeipſo, vel aliis, aliquid revelet, quod naturales Ingenii noſtri vires excedat, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia ſunt myſteria Incarnationis &amp; Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, non recuſabimus illa credere, quamvis non clarè intelligamus, nec ullo modo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimur, multa eſſe tum in immensa ejus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, tum etiam in rebus ab eo creatis, quae captum noſtrum excedant.]</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And let me add on this occaſion, that whereas the main Scruples that are ſaid to be ſuggeſted by Philoſophy againſt ſome myſterious Articles of Religion, are grounded upon this, that the <hi>Modus,</hi> as they ſpeak, of thoſe things is not clearly conceivable, or at leaſt is very hardly explicable; theſe objections are not always ſo weighty as perhaps by the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48436:38"/>confidence wherewith they are urg'd you may think them. For whereas I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to you already, that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things maintain'd by School Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, which are not contained in the Scripture, that obſervation is chiefly applicable to the things we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering; ſince in ſeveral of theſe nice Points, the Scripture affirms only the thing, and the Schoolmen are pleas'd to add the <hi>Modus:</hi> And as by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable boldneſs the School Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines determine many things without Book; ſo the ſcruples and objections that are made againſt what the Scripture really delivers, are uſually grounded upon the Erroneous or Precarious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions of the School Philoſophers, who often give the Title of Metaphyſical Truths to Conceits that do very little deſerve that name, and to which a rigid Philoſopher would perhaps think that of Sublime Nonſenſe more proper. But of this I elſewhere ſay enough, and therefore ſhall now proceed to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration I chiefly intended, <hi>viz.</hi> That from hence, <hi>That the</hi> Modus <hi>of a revealed Truth is either very hard, or not at all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable,</hi> it will not neceſſarily follow, that the thing it ſelf is irrational, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48436:38"/>the poſitive Proofs of its Truth be ſufficient in their kind. For ev'n in Natural things Philoſophers themſelves do and muſt admit ſeveral things, whereof they cannot clearly <hi>explicate</hi> or perhaps <hi>conceive</hi> the <hi>Modus.</hi> I will not here mention the Origine of Subſtantial Forms as an inſtance in this kind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though it may be a fit one as to the Peripatetick Philoſophy; yet not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that there are any ſuch Beings, I will take no further notice of them; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially becauſe for a clear Inſtance to our preſent purpoſe, we need go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than our ſelves, and conſider the Union of the Soul and Body in man. For who can Phyſically explain, <hi>both</hi> how an immaterial Subſtance ſhould be able to guide or determine, and excite the motions of a Body, and yet not be able to produce motion in it (as by dead Palſies, great Faintneſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it appears the Soul cannot,) <hi>and,</hi> which is far more difficult, how an incorporeal Subſtance ſhould receive ſuch Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the motions of a Body, as to be thereby affected with real pain and pleaſure; to which I elſewhere add ſome other properties of this Union, which, though not taken notice of, are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48436:39"/>perhaps no leſs difficult to be conceiv'd and accounted for. For how can we comprehend that there ſhould be <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> ſuch an intimate Union betwixt two ſuch diſtant Subſtances as an (In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal) Spirit and a Body, as that the former may not, when it pleaſes, quit the latter, which cannot poſſibly have any ſtrings or chains that can tye or faſten to it that which has no Body on which they may take hold. And I there ſhew, that 'tis full as difficult, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſically to explicate how theſe ſo differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beings come to be united, as how they are kept from parting at pleaſure, both the one and the other being to be reſolv'd into the meer appointment of God. And if to avoid the abſtruſeneſs of the <hi>Modus</hi> of this Conjunction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Rational Soul and the Humane Body, it be ſaid, as 'tis by the <hi>Epicure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that the former is but a certain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture of the finer and moſt ſubtle parts of the latter, the formerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd abſtruſeneſs of the Union betwixt the Soul and the Body will indeed be ſhifted off; but 'twill be by a Doctrine that will not much relieve us. For thoſe that will allow no Soul in Man but what is Corporeal, have a <hi>Modus</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48436:39"/>plain that I doubt they will alwayes leave a Riddle. For of ſuch I deſire, that they would explain to me, (who know no effects that Matter can produce but by Local Motion and Reſt, and the conſequences of it,) how meer Matter, (let them ſuppoſe it as fine as they pleaſe, and contrive it as well as they can) can make Syllogiſms, and have Conceptions of Univerſals, and invent ſpeculative Sciences and Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in a word do all thoſe things which are done by Man, and by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Animal; and he that ſhall intelligib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly explicate to me the <hi>Modus</hi> of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, framing Theories and Ratiocinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will, I confeſs, not only inſtruct me, but ſurprize me too.</p>
                     <p>And now give me leave to make this ſhort Reflection on what has been ſaid in this Section, compar'd with what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly I ſaid in the firſt Section: That if on the one hand we lay aſide all the Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational Opinions that the Schoolmen and other bold Writers have unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably father'd on Chriſtian Religion, and on the other hand all the Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conceits repugnant to Chriſtianity, which the Schoolmen and others have proofleſly father'd upon Philoſophy, the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48436:40"/>
                        <hi>ſeeming</hi> Contradictions betwixt ſolid Divinity and true Philoſophy will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be but <hi>few,</hi> as I think the <hi>Real</hi> ones will be found to be <hi>none at all.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                     <p>The next Conſideration I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is, That a thing may, if ſingly or preciſely conſider'd, appear Unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which yet may be very Credible, if conſider'd as a Part of, or a manifeſt Conſequence from, a Doctrine that is highly ſo.</p>
                     <p>Of this I could give you more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in ſeveral Arts and Sciences, than I think fit to be here ſpecifi'd; and therefore I ſhall content my ſelf to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion three or four.</p>
                     <p>When <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> tell us that the Sun, which ſeems not to us a foot broad, nor conſiderably bigger than the Moon, is above a hundred and threeſcore times bigger than the whole Globe of the Earth, which yet is forty times greater than the Moon; the thing thus naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propos'd, ſeems very Incredible. But yet, becauſe Aſtronomers very skilful in their Art, have, by finding the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diameter
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48436:40"/>of the Earth, and obſerving the Parallaxes of the Planets, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the proportion of theſe three Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be ſuch as has been mention'd, or thereabout, ev'n Learn'd and Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men of all ſorts, (Philoſophers, Divines, and others,) think it not Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity to admit what they affirm.</p>
                     <p>So the relations of Earthquakes that have reach'd divers hundreds of miles; <hi>of</hi> Eruptions of fire, that have at once overflown and burn'd vaſt Scopes of Land; <hi>of</hi> the blowing up of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains by their own fires; <hi>of</hi> the Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of new Iſlands in the Sea it ſelf, and other <hi>Prodigies of too unqueſtionable. Truth;</hi> (for I know what work Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Superſtition have made about other Prodigies:) If they were atteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by ſlight and ordinary Witneſs, they would be judg'd Incredible, but we ſcruple not to believe them, when the Relations are atteſted with ſuch Circumſtances, as make the Teſtimony as ſtrong as the things atteſted are ſtrange.</p>
                     <p>If ever you have conſider'd, what <hi>Clavius,</hi> and divers other Geometricians teach upon the ſixteenth <hi>Propoſition</hi> of the third Book of <hi>Euclide,</hi> (which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48436:41"/>contains a Theorem about the Tangent and the Circumference of a Circle,) you cannot but have taken notice, that there are ſcarce greater Paradoxes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd by Philoſophers or <hi>Divines,</hi> than you will find aſſerted by <hi>Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> themſelves. And though of late the Learned Jeſuit <hi>Tacquet,</hi> and ſome ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid <hi>Mathematicians,</hi> have queſtion'd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of thoſe things, yet ev'n what ſome of theſe ſevere Examiners confeſs to be Geometrically demonſtrable from that Propoſition, contains things ſo ſtrange, that Philoſophers themſelves, that are not well acquainted with that Propoſition and its Corollaries, can ſcarce look upon them as other than In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, or at leaſt Incredible, things; which yet, as improbable as they are conſider'd in themſelves, ev'n rigid Demonſtrators refuſe not to admit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> are legitimately deducible from an Acknowledg'd truth.</p>
                     <p>And ſo alſo among the <hi>Magnetical</hi> Phaenomena there are divers things, which being nakedly propos'd muſt ſeem altogether unfit to be believ'd, as indeed having nothing like them in all nature; whereas thoſe that are vers'd in Magnetick Philoſophy, ev'n before
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48436:41"/>they have made particular Trials of them, will look upon them as credible, becauſe, how great Paradoxes ſoever they may ſeem to others, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant and conſequent to the Doctrine of Magnetiſm, whoſe grand Axioms (from what cauſe ſoever Magnetiſms are to be deriv'd) are ſufficiently mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; and therefore a Magnetical Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher would not, though an ordinary Philoſopher would, think it unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to believe, that one part of the ſame Loadſtone ſhould draw a Needle to it, and the other part drive the ſame Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle from it; and that the Needle in a Seamans Compaſs, after having been carry'd perhaps many hunder'd Leagues (through differing Climates, and in ſtormy weather) without varying its Declination, may upon a ſudden, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manifeſt cauſe, point at ſome part of the Horizons ſeveral whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees diſtant from that which it point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to before. To which might here be added divers other ſcarce credible things, which either others or I have try'd about Magnetical Bodies; but I ſhall hereafter have occaſion to take notice of ſome of them in a fitter place.</p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:48436:42"/>
                     <p>Wherefore, when ſomething deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd in or clearly deduc'd from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is objected againſt, as a thing which it is not reaſonable to believe, we muſt not only conſider, whether, if it were not deliver'd in that Book, we ſhould upon its own ſingle Account think it fit or unworthy to be believ'd; but whether or no it is ſo improbable, that 'tis more fit to be believ'd, that all the proofs that can be brought for the Authority of the Scripture are to be Rejected, than that this thing which comes manifeſtly recommended to our belief by that Authority, is worthy to be Admitted: I ſay, <hi>manifeſtly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by that Authority,</hi> becauſe that, if the thing be not clearly deliver'd in Scripture, or be not clearly and cogent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deduc'd thence, ſo far as that clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is wanting, ſo far the thing it ſelf wants of the full Authority of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to impoſe it on our aſſent.</p>
                     <p>[Perhaps it will procure what I have ſaid the better Reception, if I add a couple of Teſtimonies not of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Bigots,</hi> no nor of any devout <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of the Church; but of two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Authors of Sects, and who in their kinds have been thought extremely
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48436:42"/>ſubtle Reaſoners, and no leſs rigid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acters of Reaſon in whatever they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
                     <p>The firſt paſſage I ſhall alledge, is the Confeſſion of <hi>Socinus,</hi> who in his ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Andreas Dudithius,</hi> ſpeaks thus: <hi>Jam verò ut rem in pauca confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, quod ad meas aliorúmve opiniones, quae novitatis praeſe ferunt ſpeciem, attinet, mihi ita videtur; ſi detur, Scriptur am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram ejus eſſe Authoritatis, ut nullo modo ei contradici poſſit, ao de interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one illius omnis duntaxat ſit ſcrupulus,</hi> (which he allows) <hi>nihil, utut veriſimile aut ratione concluſum videatur, afferri con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra eas poſſit quod ullarum ſit virium, quotieſcunque illae ſententiis atque verbis illius Libri aut rationibus liquidò inde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct is probatae atque aſſertae fuerint.</hi> Which confeſſion of <hi>Socinus</hi> is ſurpaſs'd by that of his Champion <hi>Smalcius,</hi> to be produc'd elſewhere in this Paper. The other paſſage I met with in the Excellent Monſieur <hi>Des Cartes</hi>'s Principles of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,
<note place="margin">Part. 2. Artic. 34, 35.</note> where diſcourſing of the either Infinite or Indefinite Diviſion of the Particles of Matter, which is neceſſary to make them fill exactly all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringly figur'd ſpaces, through which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48436:43"/>various motions do ſometimes make them paſs; he confeſſes (as he well may,) that the point is exceedingly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe, and yet concludes: <hi>Et quamvis quomodo fiat indefinita iſta Diviſio cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione comprehendere nequeamus, non ideo tamen debemus dubitare quin fiat, quia clarè percipimus ill am neceſſario ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui ex natura materiae nobis evidentiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè cognitâ,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
                     <p>And in this place it may be ſeaſonable as well as pertinent, to take notice of three or four particulars, which, though they be in ſome meaſure imply'd in the former general Conſideration, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be diſtinctly inculcated here, both for their importance, and becauſe they may as well be deduc'd as Corol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries from the foregoing Diſcourſe, as be confirmed by the proofs I ſhall add to each of them. Of theſe the <hi>firſt</hi> ſhall be this, that we muſt not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude a thing to be contrary to Reaſon, becauſe Learned Men profeſs or ev'n complain, that they are not able clearly to <hi>comprehend</hi> it, provided there be competent proof that it is true, and the thing be Primary or Heteroclite.</p>
                     <p>For it is not <hi>alwayes</hi> neceſſary to the making the belief of a thing Rational,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48436:43"/>that we have ſuch a Comprehenſion of the <hi>thing</hi> believ'd as may be had and juſtly required in <hi>ordinary Caſes;</hi> ſince we may be ſure of the Truth of a thing, not only by Arguments ſuggeſted by the Nature of the thing it ſelf clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood by us; but by the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Teſtimony of ſuch a Witneſs, as we know will not deceive us, and cannot (at leaſt in our Caſe) be reaſonably ſuſpected to be himſelf deceiv'd. And therefore it may in <hi>ſome Caſes</hi> ſuffice to make our belief Rational, that we clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcern ſufficient Reaſon to believe that a thing is true, whether that Reaſon ſpring from the Evidence and Cogency of the extrinſick Motives we have to believe, or from the Proofs ſuggeſted to us by what we know of the Thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, nay, though there be ſomething in the nature of that Thing, which do's puzzle and poſe our Underſtanding.</p>
                     <p>That many things that are very hard, and require a great attention, and a good judgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> made out, may yet be true, will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nifeſt from what I ſhall within a Page or two note a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout divers Geometrical Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which require, beſides a good ſtock of knowledge in thoſe matters, an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48436:44"/>invincible Patience to carry ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things along in ones Mind, and go thorow with them. That alſo there are other things, which, though they be as manifeſtly Exiſtent, as thoſe newly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd can be demonſtratively True, are yet of ſo abſtruſe a kind, that it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding difficult to frame clear and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory Notions of their Nature, we might learn, if we were inquiſitive e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, ev'n from ſome of the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious things; ſuch as, for inſtance, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Time:</hi> As to the former whereof, (<hi>Matter,</hi>) though the World and our own Bodies be made of it, yet the Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a's that are wont to be framed of it ev'n by the greateſt Clerks, are incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd with too great difficulties (ſome of which I elſewhere mention) to be eaſily acquieſc'd in by conſidering Men. And as for the latter, <hi>(Time,)</hi> though that juſtly celebrated ſaying of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, Si nemo ex me quaerat quid ſit Tempus, ſcio; ſi quaerenti explicare velim, neſcio;</hi> ſeem in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rſt part of it to own a knowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> what Time is, yet by the latter part, (wherein he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he cannot declare what it is,) I am not only allow'd to believe that he could not propoſe an intelligible Idea
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48436:44"/>of it, but invited to think that in the firſt part of the ſentence he only meant, that when he did not attentively conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Nature of it,</hi> he thought he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it, or that he knew <hi>that there is</hi> ſuch a thing as <hi>Time,</hi> though he could not explain <hi>what it is.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And indeed, though <hi>Time</hi> be that, which all Men allow to be, yet, if <hi>per impoſſibile</hi> (as the Schools ſpeak) a Man could have no other Notion or Proof of Time and Eternity, (even ſuch Eternity as muſt be conceded to ſomething,) than what he could col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect from the beſt Deſcriptions of its Nature and Properties that are wont to be given; I ſcarce doubt, but he would look upon it as an unintelligible thing, and incumber'd with too many Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be fit to be admitted into a wiſe mans Belief. And this perhaps you will grant me, if you have ever put your ſelf to the Penance of peruſing thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding Diſputes and Speculations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Eternity,</hi> that partly in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his Commentators, and partly among the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and others, are to be met with upon theſe abſtruſe Subjects. And no wonder, ſince the Learned <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> and his Followers
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48436:45"/>have very plauſibly (if not ſolidly) ſhewn, that <hi>Duration,</hi> (and Time is but Duration meaſur'd) is neither a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance nor an Accident, which they alſo hold of <hi>Space;</hi> about which the Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations among Philoſophers and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are but little, if at all, inferiour to thoſe about <hi>Time.</hi> And I the rather chooſe to mention theſe inſtances of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Space,</hi> becauſe they agree very well with what I intimated by the expreſſion of <hi>Primary</hi> or <hi>Heteroclite</hi> things.</p>
                     <p>To which may be referr'd ſome of thoſe things, that are call'd <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Supernatural,</hi> about which the ſame Conſiderations may have place, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by Reaſon of this Affinity between them, that when we treat of either, ſome Proofs may in certain Caſes be ſufficient, in ſpite of ſuch Objections, as in other (and more ordinary Caſes) would invalidate Arguments ſeemingly as ſtrong as thoſe Proofs.</p>
                     <p>If it be here objected, That I am too bold in venturing without the Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or Authority of Learned Men, to introduce ſo great a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt other things and thoſe which I call <hi>Primary</hi> and <hi>Heteroclite:</hi> I anſwer,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48436:45"/>That I ſhall not ſolicitouſly enquire, whether any others have had the ſame thoughts that I propos'd; ſince, whether they be new or no, they ought not to be rejected, if they be Rational.</p>
                     <p>And I have this inducement to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that there ought to be in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes a great difference between them and other things, and conſequently between the judgments we make of the ways of arguing about them, and about other things; ſo that they are exceeding dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be clearly conceiv'd and expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by our imperfect Faculties, and by that difficulty apt to make what Men ſay of them, though true, to be leſs ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory and acquieſced in, than things not more true or rational, ſuggeſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enquiries about Subjects more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, or which are at leaſt more propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate to our Faculties: For, thoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe things, of which we have been ſpeaking, being ſuch, as either have no proper and clear <hi>Genus,</hi> by the help of which they may be comprehended, or have not any thing in Nature, that is (ſufficiently) like them, by a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to which we may conceive them; or being perhaps both <hi>Primary</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroclite</hi> too, as not being deriv'd from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48436:46"/>the common Phyſical Cauſes of other things, and having a Nature widely dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from the reſt of things; 'tis no wonder, that our limited and imperfect Underſtandings ſhould not be able to reach to a full and clear Comprehenſion of them; but ſhould be ſwallow'd up with the Scruples and Difficulties that may be ſuggeſted by a bold and nice en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into things, to which there ſeems to belong, in ſome reſpect or other, a kind of Infinity.</p>
                     <p>Upon theſe, and other Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of kin to them, I count it not irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, to think that things <hi>Primary</hi> and <hi>Heteroclite,</hi> as alſo by a parity of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſome things Immaterial and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, may be ſufficiently prov'd in their kind, if there be ſuch a poſitive proof of them as would be competent and ſatisfactory, in caſe there were no conſiderable Objections made againſt the thing prov'd (eſpecially ſuppoſing that the aſſerted Doctrine be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred with much greater inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies than the contrary Doctrine, or than any other, propos'd concerning that Subject:) Nay, I know not, why we may not, in judging of Primary and of Immaterial things, ſafely enough prefer
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48436:46"/>that Opinion, which has the more Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>Poſitive Proofs,</hi> though it ſeem lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſomewhat the greater inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies; becauſe in ſuch caſes our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is gratify'd with what it moſt requires in all caſes, that is compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Poſitive</hi> Inducements to aſſent; and it is not confounded by the Objections, becauſe a diſability to anſwer them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and fully may very well proceed either from the too abſtruſe Nature of the thing, or the limitedneſs and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our humane Intellects.</p>
                     <p>And thus we may render a Reaſon, why, when we diſcourſe of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common Matters, we may ſometimes reaſonably acquieſce in proofs in ſpight of ſuch Objections as in ordinary caſes would be prevailing ones. For the things, about which theſe proofs are converſant, being <hi>Primary</hi> or <hi>Heteroclite,</hi> or of as abſtruſe a Nature as if they were ſo, it too often happens, that, what Opinion ſoever we chooſe about them, we muſt admit ſomething that is incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with great difficulties, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will be liable to great Objections, that perhaps will never be directly and ſatisfactorily anſwer'd. And ſince it may fare thus with us, where two oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48436:47"/>Opinions are contradictory, we may conclude, that thoſe difficulties will not cogently evince the falſity of a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Opinion, which are but ſuch, that the ſame, or as great, may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt another, that either is manifeſtly or confeſſedly a Truth, or which muſt neceſſarily be admitted to be one, if the contrary Theological Tenet be ſuppos'd not to be one.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Another Corollary that may be drawn from the Diſcourſe that afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us the former, may be this; That it may not be unreaſonable to believe a thing, though its <hi>Proof</hi> be very difficult to be underſtood. To manifeſt this, I ſhall need no other Argument, than what may be afforded by divers Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical and other Mathematical Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations; ſome of which are fetch'd by intermediate Concluſions from Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſo very remote, and require ſo long a <hi>ſeries</hi> of <hi>Mediums</hi> to be employ'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, that <hi>not only</hi> a Man that were of <hi>Pilate</hi>'s temper, who having ask'd Him that could beſt tell him, <hi>What is Truth,</hi> would not ſtay awhile to be ſatisfi'd about his Inquiry, would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he reaches half way to the End of the Demonſtration, or perhaps of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48436:47"/>
                        <hi>Lemma's,</hi> be quite diſcourag'd from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding any further; <hi>but</hi> ev'n ſedulous and heedful Peruſers do find themſelves oftentimes unable to carry along ſuch a chain of Inferences in their minds, as clearly to diſcern whether the whole Ratiocination be coherent, and all the particulars have their due ſtrength and connection. And if you pleaſe to make a Tryal upon ſome of the Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Vitellio,</hi> or ev'n of <hi>Clavius,</hi> that I can direct you to, I doubt they will put you to the full Exerciſe of your Patience, and quite tire your Attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And though the modern Algebriſts by their Excellent way of expreſſing Quantities by Symbols, have ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg'd Geometrical and Arithmetical Demonſtrations, that by the help of <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> 'tis ſometimes eaſie to Demonſtrate that in a Line, which in the ordinary way would require a whole Page, (as our moſt Learned Friend Dr. <hi>Ward</hi> has ingeniouſly ſhewn, by giving the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of about twenty of Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Theorems in leſs than ſo many Lines;) yet ſome Demonſtrable Truths are ſo abſtruſe, that ev'n in the Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical way Men need more attention to diſcern them, than moſt Men would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48436:48"/>in any Speculation whatſoever. And <hi>Des-Cartes</hi> himſelf, as famous and expert a Maſter as he was in this way, confeſſes in a Letter to one of his Friends, that the Solution of a Problem in <hi>Pappus</hi> coſt him no leſs than ſix weeks ſtudy; though now, moſt Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Demonſtrations do indeed ſeem far ſhorter than they are, becauſe that <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clid</hi>'s <hi>Elements</hi> being generally receiv'd among Mathematicians, all his Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſo many <hi>Lemmata,</hi> which need be but refer'd to in the Margin, being known and demonſtrated already. By all which it may appear, that, granting ſome Theological Truths to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of by many as things ſo myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and abſtruſe, that they cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily diſcern the force of thoſe Proofs, that <hi>Des-Cartes,</hi> and other ſubtile Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators have propos'd to evince them; yet if other Learned Men that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Eſtimators, and are accuſtomed to bring much Patience and Attention to the diſcernment of difficult and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Truths, profeſs themſelves ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd with them, the Probations may yet be cogent, notwithſtanding the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to have their ſtrength apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For if ſuch a difficulty ought to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48436:48"/>paſs for a mark that a Ratiocination is not valid, no Reaſonings will be found fitter to be rejected or diſtruſted, than many of thoſe whoſe Cogency has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd ſuch a Repute to Mathematical Demonſtrations.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. It may alſo be deduc'd from the foregoing diſcourſe, That 'tis not <hi>always</hi> againſt Reaſon to embrace an Opinion which may be incumbred with a great Difficulty, or liable to an Objection not eaſie to be ſolv'd; eſpecially if the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject be ſuch, that other Opinions about it avoid not either the ſame Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, or as great ones. The <hi>firſt</hi> part of what is ſaid in this Conſideration, will often follow from the Suppoſition made in the precedent Diſcourſe. For thoſe things that render a Doctrine or Aſſertion difficult to be conceiv'd and explain'd, will eaſily ſupply the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of it with Objections againſt it.</p>
                     <p>And as for the <hi>latter, viz.</hi> the Clauſe which takes notice that the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to which 'tis annex'd, will chiefly take place in that ſort of Opinions that are ſpecifi'd in it; it will need but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of diſtinct Proof.</p>
                     <p>For 'tis manifeſt enough, that if the Subject or Object, about which the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48436:49"/>propos'd is converſant, be ſuch, that not only the contradictory Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but others alſo, are obnoxious ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ſame Inconveniencies, or to others that are equal or greater; the difficulties that are urg'd againſt a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Doctrine, may (as hath been ſhewn already in the firſt Corollary) be rationally enough attributed, not to the unreaſonableneſs of the Opinion, but to ſomewhat elſe.</p>
                     <p>The laſt Conſectary, that (as I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated) may be deduc'd from the precedent Diſcourſe, is, That 'tis not always Unreaſonable to believe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Theological for a Truth, which (I do not ſay is <hi>truly inconſiſtent with,</hi> but) <hi>we do not clearly diſcern to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port very well with ſomething elſe that we alſo take for a Truth,</hi> or perhaps that is one indeed; if the Theological Tenet be ſufficiently prov'd in its kind, and be of that ſort of things that we have been of late and are yet diſcourſing of.</p>
                     <p>The generality of our Philoſophers, as well as Divines, believe, That God has a foreknowledge of all future Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies; and yet how a certain Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can conſiſt with the Free-will of Man, (which yet is generally grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48436:49"/>him, in things meerly Moral or Civil,) is ſo difficult to diſcern, that the <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> are wont to deny ſuch things, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the will of free Agents, to be the proper Objects of Omniſcience; and the Head of the Remonſtrants, though a very ſubtle Writer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes that he knows not, how clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make out the conſiſtency of Gods Preſcience and Mans freedom; both which he yet confeſſes to be Truths, being compell'd to acknowledge the former, (for the latter is evident,) as well by the Infiniteneſs that muſt be aſcrib'd to Gods Perfections, as by the Prophetick Predictions, whereby ſuch contingent Events have been actually foretold. And the reconcilement of theſe Truths is not a difficulty peculiar to the Chriſtian Religion, but concerns ſpeculative Men in all Religions, who acknowledge the Deity to be infinitely perfect, and allow Man, as they do, to be a free Agent.</p>
                     <p>[But I have made this Section ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix already, that I muſt not enlarge on this third particular. And therefore I ſhall ſhut it up with an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Des-Cartes,</hi> which may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd not only to it, but to almoſt all
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48436:50"/>that has been diſcours'd in this Section, and indeed to a great part of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. He then in an Epiſtle, that came not forth till ſome years after the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters death, ſpeaks thus to the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Adverſary to whom 'tis addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: <hi>As I have often ſaid, when the Queſtion is about things that relate to God, or to what is Infinite, we muſt not conſider what we can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend of them,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Volume 2. Letter 16.</note> 
                        <hi>(ſince we know that they ought not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by us) but only what we can conceive of them, or can attain to by any certain Reaſon or Argument.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                     <p>And now 'tis time to advance to one of the main Conſiderations I had to propoſe to you concerning the Subject of this Letter, and it is this; That when we are to judge, whether a thing be contrary to Reaſon or not, there is a great deal of difference, whether we take Reaſon for the Faculty furniſh'd only with its own innate Principle, and ſuch Notions as are generally obvious, (nay, and if you pleaſe, with this or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48436:50"/>that Philoſophical Theory;) or for the Faculty illuminated by Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, eſpecially that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in the Books commonly call'd the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To clear and inforce this the better, I ſhall invite you to take notice with me of the two following particulars.</p>
                     <p>We may then in the <hi>firſt</hi> place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, That ev'n in things meerly Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Men do not think it at all Irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, to believe divers ſuch things upon extrinſecal Proofs, eſpecially the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the skilful, as, if it were not for that Teſtimony, a Man, though born with good parts, and poſſibly very Learn'd in the Peripatetick or ſome other particular Philoſophy, would look upon as Irrational to be believ'd, and contrary to the Laws of Nature.</p>
                     <p>Of this I ſhall give you ſome Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of the <hi>Loadſtone,</hi> and particularly ſuch as theſe; <hi>That</hi> the Loadſtone, though (as was above inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated) with one part it will draw, yet with another the ſame ſtone will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the ſame point of the ſame excited Needle; and yet at the ſame time be fit to attract either point of another Needle that never came near a Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48436:51"/>before: <hi>That</hi> though it be the Loadſtone that imparts an attractive virtue to the Iron, yet when the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone is cap'd, as they call'd it, and ſo a piece of Iron (and conſequently a diſtance) is interpos'd betwixt the ſtone and the weight to be rais'd, it will take up by many times more than if it be it ſelf apply'd immediately thereunto, inſomuch that <hi>Merſennus</hi> relates
<note n="*" place="margin">In his little Tract <hi>de Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netis Propri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus.</hi> p. m. 350.</note>, that (if there be no miſtake,) he had a Loadſtone that of <hi>it ſelf</hi> would take up but half an Ounce of Iron, which when <hi>arm'd</hi> (or cap'd) would lift up ten Pounds, which (ſays he) exceeded the former weight three hundred and twenty times: <hi>That</hi> a Mariners Needle, being once touch'd with a vigorous Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, will afterwards, when freely poiz'd, turn it ſelf North and South; and if it be by force made to regard the Eaſt and Weſt, or any other points of the Compaſs, as ſoon as 'tis left at liberty, 'twill of its ſelf return to its former Poſition: <hi>That</hi> a Loadſtone float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on water, will as well come to, and follow a piece of, Iron that is kept from advancing towards it; as, when it ſelf
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48436:51"/>is fix'd, and the Iron at liberty, 'twill draw that Metal to it: <hi>That</hi> without any ſenſible alteration in the Agent or the Patient, the Loadſtone will in a trice communicate all its virtues to a piece of Steel, and enable that to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate them to another piece of the ſame Metal: <hi>That</hi> if a Loadſtone, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been markt at one end, be cut long-wiſe according to its <hi>Axis,</hi> and one Segment be freely ſuſpended over the other, the halves of the markt end, that touch'd one another before, will not now lie together, but the lower will drive away the upper; and that which regarded the North in the markt end of the intire Loadſtone, will join with that extreme of the lower half, which in the intire ſtone regarded the South: <hi>That</hi> (as appears by this laſt nam'd Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) there are the ſame Magnetical Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in the ſeparated parts of a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, as in the intire ſtone; and if it be cut, or even rudely broken into a great many parts or fragments, every one of theſe portions, though perhaps not ſo big as a Corn of Wheat, will, if I may ſo ſpeak, ſet up for its ſelf, and have its own Northern and Southern Poles, and become a little Magnet, <hi>ſui juris,</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:48436:52"/>upon the ſtone from which 'twas ſever'd, and from all its other parts: <hi>That,</hi> if a Loadſtone be skilfully made Spherical, this little Magnetick Globe, very fitly by our <hi>Gilbert</hi> call'd a <hi>Terrella,</hi> will not only, being freely plac'd, turn North and South, and retain that Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but have its Poles, its Meridians, its <hi>Aequator</hi> &amp;c. upon good grounds deſignable upon it, as they are upon the great Globe of the Earth. And this will hold, whether the <hi>Terrella</hi> be great or ſmall.</p>
                     <p>I might not only much encreaſe the number of theſe odd Magnetical <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena's,</hi> but add others about other Subjects: But theſe may ſuffice to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt to us this Reflection, That there is no doubt to be made, but that a Man, who never had the opportunity to ſee or hear of Magnetical Experiments, would look upon theſe as contrary to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Nature, and therefore to the Dictates of Reaſon, as (accordingly) ſome Learned <hi>Ariſtotelians,</hi> to whom I had occaſion to propoſe ſome of them, rejected them as Incredible. And I doubt not, but I could frame as plauſible Arguments from the meer Axioms of Philoſophers, and the Doctrine of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophick
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48436:52"/>Schools againſt ſome Magne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> which Experience hath ſatisfi'd me of, as are wont to be drawn from the ſame Topicks againſt the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Articles of Faith; ſince among the ſtrange Properties of the Loadſtone there are ſome, which are not only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable and ſtupendious, but ſeem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Dictates of the received Philoſophy and the courſe of Nature. For, whereas Natural Bodies, how ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſoever, require ſome particular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in the <hi>Medium</hi> through which their Corpuſcles are to be diffus'd, or their Actions tranſmitted, ſo that Light it ſelf, whether it be a moſt ſubtile Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or a naked Quality, is reſiſted by all opacous <hi>Mediums,</hi> and the very <hi>effluvia</hi> of Amber and other Electricks will not permeate the thinneſt Glaſs, or even a ſheet of fine Paper; yet the Loadſtone readily performing his Operations through all kind of <hi>Mediums,</hi> without excepting Glaſs it ſelf.</p>
                     <p>If the Poles of two Magnetick Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles do both of them regard the North, another Philoſopher would conclude them to have a <hi>Sympathy,</hi> at leaſt to be unlikely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſagree; and yet, if he bring theſe Extremes of the ſame Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48436:53"/>within the reach of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, one will preſently drive away the other as if there were a powerful <hi>Antipathy</hi> between them.</p>
                     <p>A ſomewhat long Needle being plac'd horizontally, and exactly poiz'd upon the point of a Pin, if you gently touch one end with the Pole of a vigorous Magnet, that end ſhall manifeſtly dip or ſtoop, though you often take it off the Pin, and put it on again. And this inclination of the Needle will continue many years, and yet there is not only no other ſenſible change made in the Metal by the Contact of the Loadſtone; but one end has requir'd a durable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponderancy, though the other be not lighter, nor the whole Needle heavier than before. And the <hi>Inclination</hi> of the Magnetick Needle may be by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other touch of the Loadſtone taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without leſsning the weight of the part that is depriv'd of it.</p>
                     <p>The Operation that in a trice the Loadſtone has on a Mariners Needle, though it makes no ſenſible change in it, or weakens the Loadſtone it ſelf, will not be loſt, though you carry it as far as the Southern Hemiſphere; but it will not be the ſame in all places, but in ſome
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48436:53"/>the Magnetick Needle will point di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly at the North, in others 'twill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate or <hi>decline</hi> ſome degrees towards the Eaſt or the Weſt: And, which ſeems yet more ſtrange, the ſame Needle in the ſame place will not always regard the ſame point of the Compaſs, but, lookt on at diſtant times, may vary from the true Meridian, ſometimes to the Weſt, and afterwards to the Eaſt.</p>
                     <p>All the communicable virtues of the Magnet may be imparted to Iron, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any actual Contact of the two Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but barely by approaching in a convenient way the Iron to the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone for a few moments. And the Metal may likewiſe be depriv'd of thoſe virtues in a trice, without any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Contact by the ſame or another Loadſtone.</p>
                     <p>If you mark one end of a Rod, or other oblong piece of Iron, that never came near a Magnet, and hold it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicularly, you may at pleaſure, and in the hundreth part of a minute, make it become the North or South Pole of a Magnetical Body. For if, when 'tis held upright, you apply to the bottom of it the North-extreme of an excited and well-poiz'd Needle, the lower end
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:48436:54"/>of the Iron will drive away that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme, which yet will be drawn by the upper end of the ſame Iron. And if by inverting you make this lower end the uppermoſt, it will not attract, but repel the ſame Lilly or North-point of the Needle, juſt under which it is to be perpendicularly held.</p>
                     <p>Though, <hi>vis unita fortior,</hi> be a receiv'd Rule among Naturaliſts; yet oftentimes, if a Magnet be cut into pieces, theſe will take up and ſuſtain much more Iron than the intire ſtone was able to do.</p>
                     <p>If of two good Loadſtones the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer be much bigger, and on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſtronger than the other, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er will draw a piece of Iron, and retain it much more ſtrongly than the leſſer; and yet, when the Iron ſticks faſt to the greater and ſtronger Loadſtone, the leſſer and weaker may draw the Iron from it, and take it quite away.</p>
                     <p>Theſe <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> (to mention now no more,) are ſo repugnant to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſentiments of Naturaliſts, and the ordinary courſe of things, that, if ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently to any Teſtimony of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence theſe Magnetical Properties had been propos'd to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf, he would probably have judg'd them ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48436:54"/>things, as repugnant to the Laws of Nature: Nevertheleſs, though it ſeems incredible, that the bare touch of a Loadſtone <hi>ſhould impart</hi> to the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Needle a Property, which, (as far as we know,) nothing in the whole World that is not Magnetical can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate or poſſeſs; and ſhould ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate (as Men ſuppoſe) upon it at three or four thouſand Leagues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; yet this is believ'd by the Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pateticks themſelves upon the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe Navigators that have ſail'd to the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> and divers even of the more rigid of the modern Philoſophers believe more than this, upon the Teſtimony of <hi>Gilbert, Cabaeus, Kircherus,</hi> and other Learned Magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Writers, who have affirmed theſe things; moſt of which I can alſo averr to you upon my own knowledge.</p>
                     <p>Thus the <hi>Habitableneſs of the Torrid Zone,</hi> though (as I lately noted) upon probable grounds deny'd by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the generality of Philoſophers for many Ages; yet not only that, but its Populouſneſs is now confidently belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the <hi>Peripatetick</hi> Schoolmen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who never were there.</p>
                     <p>And though <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and ſome other
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48436:55"/>eminent Aſtronomers, did with great care and skill, and by the help of Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, as well as Obſervations, frame a Theory of the Planets ſo plauſibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd, that moſt of the ſucceeding Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicians for 12 or 14 Ages acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſc'd in it; yet almoſt all the modern Philoſophers and Aſtronomers, that have ſearch'd into theſe matters with a readineſs to believe their Eyes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Reaſon to act freely, have been forc'd, if not to reject the whole Theory, yet at leaſt to alter it quite, as to the Number and Order of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, though theſe laſt nam'd Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſometimes <hi>ſolely,</hi> and always <hi>mainly</hi> built upon the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd to us by two or three pieces of glaſs plac'd in a long hollow Cane, and honour'd with the name of a <hi>Teleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The laſt of the two things I invited you to conſider with me, is this, That when we are to judge, which of two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing Opinions is moſt Rational, <hi>i.e.</hi> to be judg'd moſt agreeable to right Reaſon, we ought to give ſentence, not for that which the Faculty, furniſh'd only with ſuch and ſuch Notions, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vulgar or borrow'd from this or
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48436:55"/>that Sect of Philoſophers, would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, but that which is prefer'd by the Faculty furniſh'd either with all the Evidence requiſite or advantagious to make it give a right Judgment in the caſe lying before it; or, when that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had, with the beſt and fulleſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations that it can procure.</p>
                     <p>This is ſo evident by its own light, that your Friend might look upon it as an affront to his Judgment, if I ſhould go about ſolicitouſly to prove it. And therefore I ſhall only advertiſe you, that, provided the Information be ſuch as a man has juſt cauſe to believe, and perceives that he clearly underſtands, it will not alter the caſe, <hi>whether</hi> he have it by Reaſon, as that is taken for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty furniſh'd but with its inbred No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and the more common Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>or</hi> by ſome Philoſophical Theory, <hi>or</hi> by Experiments purpoſely devis'd, <hi>or</hi> by Teſtimony Humane or Divine, which laſt we call <hi>Revelation.</hi> For all theſe are but differing ways of informing the Underſtanding, and of ſignifying to it the ſame thing; as the Sight and the Touch may aſſure a Man, that a Body is ſmooth or rough, or in motion or at reſt; (and in ſome other inſtances ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48436:56"/>ſenſes diſcover to us the ſame Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which is therefore call'd <hi>Objectum Commune;</hi>) and provided theſe Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations have the conditions lately inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, which way ſoever the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding receives them, it may ſafely reaſon and build Opinions upon them.</p>
                     <p>Aſtronomers have within theſe 100 years obſerv'd, that a Star hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red among the Fix'd ones for ſome time, and having afterwards diſappear'd, has yet ſome years after that, ſhew'd it ſelf again. And though, as to this ſurpriſing <hi>Phaenomenon,</hi> our Experimental Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers could have contributed nothing to the producing it, and though 'tis quite out of all the received Syſtems of the Heavens that Aſtronomers have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto deliver'd; yet the Star it ſelf may be a true Celeſtial light, and may allow us to Philoſophize upon it, and draw Inferences from the Diſcoveries it makes us; as well as we can from the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of thoſe Stars that are not extraordinary, and of thoſe Falling Stars that are within our own Ken and Region.</p>
                     <p>That the Supernatural things, ſaid to be perform'd by <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Evil Spirits,</hi> might, if true, ſupply us with <hi>Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
                        <pb n="87" facs="tcp:48436:56"/>and <hi>Mediums</hi> whereby to conſtitute and prove Theories, as well as the <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena</hi> of meer nature, ſeems tacitely indeed, but yet ſufficiently, to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd, by thoſe modern Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, that care not to take any other way to decline the Conſequences that may be drawn from ſuch Relations, than ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitouſly to ſhew, that the Relations themſelves are all (as I fear moſt of them are) falſe, and occaſion'd by the Credulity or Impoſture of Men.</p>
                     <p>But not to do any more than glance at theſe matters, let us proceed upon what is more unqueſtionable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that, ſince ev'n our moſt Critical Philoſophers do admit many of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhing Attributes of Magnetick Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which themſelves never had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſee, upon the Teſtimony of <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> and others, who never were able to give the true cauſes of them; becauſe they look upon thoſe Relators as honeſt Men, and judicious enough not to be impos'd upon as to the matter of Fact: Since (I ſay) ſuch amazing things are believ'd by ſuch ſevere Naturaliſts, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Authority of Men who did not know the intimate nature of Magnetick Bodies; and ſince theſe ſtrange <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi>
                        <pb n="88" facs="tcp:48436:57"/>are not only aſſented to as true by the Philoſophers we ſpeak of, but many Philoſophical conſequences are without haeſitancy deduc'd from them, without any blemiſh to the judgment of thoſe that give their Aſſent both to the Things and the Inferences; why ſhould it be contrary to Reaſon to believe the Teſtimony of God either about his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which He can <hi>beſt,</hi> and He alone can <hi>fully</hi> know, or about the things which either he himſelf has done, as the Creation of the World and of Man; or which he means to do, as the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World, (whether the whole World, or our great <hi>Vortex</hi> only, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute not,) and the raiſing both of good and bad Men to life again, to receive Rewards and Puniſhments, according to their Demerits. For methinks that Apoſtle argues very well, who ſays, <hi>If we receive the teſtimony of men,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 John. v. 9.</note> 
                        <hi>the teſtimony of God is greater;</hi> eſpecially about ſuch things concerning his own Nature, Will, and Purpoſes, as 'tis evident that Reaſon, by its own unaſſiſted light, cannot give us the knowledge of.</p>
                     <p>So that we Chriſtians in aſſenting to Doctrines upon the account of Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48436:57"/>need not, nor do not, reject the Authority of Reaſon, but only appeal from Reaſon to it ſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> from Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as it is more <hi>ſlightly,</hi> to its Dictates, as 'tis more <hi>fully</hi> inform'd. Of which two ſorts of Dictates there is nothing more rational, than to prefer the latter to the former.</p>
                     <p>And for my part I am apt to think, that, if what has been repreſented in this <hi>Section</hi> were duly conſider'd, this alone would very much contribute to prevent or anſwer moſt of the Objections, that make ſuch of the Queſtioners of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as are not reſolutely vitious, entertain ſuch hard thoughts of ſome Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, as if they were directly repugnant to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For, (as we were obſerving) <hi>that</hi> is not to be look'd on as the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Reaſon, that is pronounc'd ev'n by a rational Man according to a Set of Notions, though the Inferences from theſe would be rational, in caſe there were nothing elſe fit to be taken into conſideration by him that judges; but <hi>that</hi> is rather to be look'd upon as the judgment of Reaſon, which takes in the moſt Information procurable, that is pertinent to the things under conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48436:58"/>And therefore Men, though otherwiſe learn'd and witty, ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not equal Eſtimators of the caſe of thoſe that believe the Articles we ſpeak of, when they pronounce them to aſſent Irrationally, becauſe the things they aſſent to cannot be demonſtrated or maintain'd by meer natural Reaſon, and would probably be rejected by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus, Epicurus, Ariſtotle,</hi> or any other of the ancient Philoſophers, to whom they ſhould be nakedly propos'd, and whoſe judgment ſhould be deſir'd about them. For, although this Allegation would ſignifie much, if we pretended to prove what we believe only by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from the nature of the thing aſſented to; yet it will not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie much in our caſe, wherein we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to prove what we believe, <hi>chiefly</hi> by Divine Teſtimony, and therefore ought not to be concluded guilty of an Irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Aſſent, unleſs it can be ſhewn, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Divine Teſtimony is not duly challeng'd by us for the main of our Religion; or that in the particular Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles we father ſomething on that Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which is not contain'd in it, or rightly deducible from it. And to put us upon the proving our particular Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48436:58"/>of Faith, ſufficiently deliver'd in the Scriptures, and not knowable without Revelation, by Arguments meerly natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, without taking notice of thoſe we can bring for the proof of that Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on whoſe account we embrace thoſe Articles, is to challenge a Man to a Duel, upon condition he ſhall make no uſe of his beſt weapons; and is as unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as if a Schoolman ſhould chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge your Friend to prove, that the <hi>Torrid Zone</hi> is inhabited, againſt the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that the <hi>Ariſtotelians</hi> are wont to give to prove it uninhabitable, without allowing him to make uſe of the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Navigators, who aſſure us of the conſtant <hi>Briſes</hi> that daily ventilate the Air, and qualifie that heat which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would not be ſupported, and who furniſh us with thoſe other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances whereon to build our proofs, which we, that were never there, can have but by Relation.</p>
                     <p>And indeed, the limitations, that Chriſtian Religion <hi>puts</hi> to ſome of the dictates of Philoſophy, which were wont to be admitted in a more general and unreſtrained Senſe, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines about God and the Soul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that it <hi>ſuperadds</hi> to thoſe which the light of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48436:59"/>Nature might lead Men to about the ſame Subjects; though to ſome they may ſeem injurious to Philoſophy and Reaſon, are as little unkind to either, as is the Gardener to a Crab-ſtock, or ſome ſuch other wild Plant, when by cutting off ſome of the Branches, and by making a ſlit in the Bark, that he may graft on it a Pare-main, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choice Apples, by this ſeemingly hard uſage he brings it to bear much nobler fruit, than, if left to its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural condition, it ever would have done.</p>
                     <p>I know not, whether to all that hath been ſaid in this <hi>Section.</hi> I may not add thus much further, that it ſometimes happens, that thoſe very things, which at firſt were propos'd to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and believ'd upon the ſcore of Revelation, are afterward aſſented to by it upon the account of meer Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. To which purpoſe I conſider, that not any of the ancient Philoſophers, nay (as far as I have read) ev'n of thoſe that believ'd God to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the World, dream'd, that He created Matter of nothing, but only form'd the World out of praeexiſtent Matter, whereas Chriſtian Divines uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48436:59"/>teach as an Article of Faith, That, beſides what they call a mediate Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as when Fiſhes were made out of the water, or <hi>Adam</hi>'s body was made out of the earth, there was an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Production of Matter it ſelf out of nothing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                     <p>After what has been hitherto diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd, it may be ſeaſonable to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what kind of Probation, or what degree of Evidence may reaſonably be thought ſufficient to make the Chriſtian Religion thought fit to be embrac'd.</p>
                     <p>Perhaps I ſhall not need to tell you, that, beſides the Demonſtrations wont to be treated of in vulgar Logick, there are among Philoſophers three diſtinct, whether <hi>kinds</hi> or <hi>degrees,</hi> of Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. For there is a <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> Demonſtration, as we may call that, where the Concluſion is manifeſtly built on thoſe general Metaphyſical Axioms that can never be other than true; ſuch as <hi>Nihil poteſt ſimul eſſe &amp; non eſſe; Non Entis nullae ſunt Proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Reales,</hi> &amp;c. There are alſo <hi>Phyſical</hi>
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:48436:60"/>Demonſtrations, where the Concluſion is evidently deduc'd from Phyſical Principles; ſuch as are, <hi>Ex nihilo nihil fit. Null a ſubſtantia in nihilum redigitur, &amp;c.</hi> which are not ſo abſolutely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain as the former, becauſe, if there be a God, He may (at leaſt for ought we know) be able to create and annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Subſtances; and yet are held un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable by the ancient Naturaliſts, who ſtill ſuppoſe them in their Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And laſtly, there are <hi>Moral</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, ſuch as thoſe where the Concluſion is built either upon ſome one <hi>ſuch</hi> proof cogent in its kind; or ſome concurrence of Probabilities that it cannot be but allowed, ſuppoſing the truth of the moſt receiv'd Rules of Prudence and Principles of Practical Philoſophy.</p>
                     <p>And this <hi>third</hi> kind of Probation, though it come behind the two others in certainty, yet it is the ſureſt guide, which the <hi>Actions of Men,</hi> though not their <hi>Contemplations,</hi> have regularly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd them to follow. And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of a <hi>Moral</hi> Demonſtration are the ſureſt that Men aſpire to, not only in the conduct of private Mens affairs, but in the Government of States, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:48436:60"/>ev'n of the greateſt Monarchies and Empires. And this is conſiderable in <hi>Moral</hi> Demonſtrations, that ſuch may conſiſt, and be as it were made up of particulars, that are each of them but probable; of which the Laws eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht by God himſelf among his own People, as well as the practice of our Courts of Juſtice here in <hi>England,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us a manifeſt inſtance in the caſe of Murder, and ſome other Criminal Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For, though the Teſtimony of a <hi>ſingle</hi> Witneſs ſhall not ſuffice to prove the accus'd party guilty of Murder; yet the Teſtimony of <hi>two</hi> Witneſſes, though but of equal Credit, that is, a ſecond Teſtimony added to the firſt, though of it ſelf never a whit more credible than the former, ſhall ordinarily ſuffice to prove a Man guilty; becauſe it is thought reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that, though each Teſtimony <hi>ſingle</hi> be but probable, yet a concurrence of ſuch Probabilities (which ought in Reaſon to be attributed to the Truth of what they jointly tend to prove) may well amount to a Moral certainty, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch a certainty as may warrant the Judge to proceed to the ſentence of death a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Indicted party.</p>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:48436:61"/>
                     <p>To apply theſe things now to the <hi>Chriſtian Religion:</hi> If you conſider, with how much approbation from diſcerning Men that judicious Obſervation of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> has been entertain'd, where he ſays, that 'tis as unskilful and improper a thing to require <hi>Mathematical</hi> Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations in <hi>Moral</hi> Affairs, as to take up with Moral Arguments in matters Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical; you will not deny, but that thoſe Articles of the Chriſtian Religion that can be prov'd by a Moral, though not by a Metaphyſical or Phyſical, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, may without any blemiſh to a Man's Reaſon be aſſented to; and that conſequently (by vertue of the foregoing Conſiderations) thoſe other Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, that are clearly and legitimately deducible from the ſo demonſtrated Truths, may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe without diſparagement be aſſented to.</p>
                     <p>We may alſo here conſider further, That the chooſing or refuſing to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Chriſtian Religion, which is not propos'd to us only as a Syſtem of Speculative Doctrines, but alſo as a Body of Laws, according to which it teaches us, that God commands us to worſhip Him, and regulate our Lives;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:48436:61"/>the embracing, <hi>I ſay,</hi> or not embracing this Religion, is an act of humane choice, and therefore ought to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd according to the dictates of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Now, though in matters that very much import us, we may wiſh for and endeavor after ſuch Reaſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to determine our Reſolves, as may amount to Moral Demonſtrations; yet Prudence will not always require, that we ſhould refuſe to act upon Arguments of a leſs Cogency than Moral Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations. For oftentimes in humane Affairs it ſo falls out, that divers hazards or other inconveniences will attend whatever reſolution we take; and in that caſe, all that Prudence requires, or can enable us to do, is, to take that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution which upon the whole matter ſeems to be preferable to any other; though that which is thus prefer'd, may perhaps be liable to ſome Objection that cannot be directly anſwer'd, but only obliquely, by the preponderancy of the Arguments that perſuade the choice againſt which the Objection is made.</p>
                     <p>But here perhaps you will tell me, that the ſafeſt way in a caſe of ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, is to ſuſpend an action that is
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48436:62"/>every way attended with difficulties, and to forbear either embracing or reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chriſtian Religion, till the truth or falſeneſs of it come to appear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and unqueſtionable.</p>
                     <p>To which I anſwer, that indeed in matters of bare Speculation, about which our <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings</hi> only need to be converſant, the ſuſpenſion of Aſſent is not only practicable, but uſually the ſafeſt way; but <hi>Des-Cartes</hi> himſelf, who has been the greateſt Example and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcator of this Suſpenſion, declares, that he would have it practis'd onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout humane <hi>Speculations,</hi> not about hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>Actions; Sed haec interim dubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ad ſolam</hi> contemplationem <hi>veritatis reſtringenda; non quantum ad uſum vitae: quia perſaepe rerum agendarum occaſio praeteriret, antequam nos dubiis noſtris exolvere poſſemus. Non raro quod tantum eſt veriſimile cogimur amplecti, vel etiam interdum, etſi è duobus unum altero ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſimiliùs non appareat, alterutrum tamen eligere.</hi> And in ſome of his other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings he ſpeaks ſo much to ſhew, that 'tis unreaſonable to expect in matters, where embracing or rejecting a courſe that requires practice is neceſſary, ſuch a certainty as he judges neceſſary to make
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48436:62"/>a true Philoſopher acquieſce in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Propoſitions about ſpeculative matters, that I find by one of his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that he was vehemently accus'd for having taught, that Men need not have as ſure grounds for chooſing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and avoiding vitious courſes, as for determining about things meerly Notional.</p>
                     <p>And here let me obſerve to you the difference, that I take notice of in the caſes where we are put upon delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whether we will chooſe or refuſe a thing propos'd. For it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to us, either as a proffer on whoſe acceptance an advantage may be hop'd, or as a duty, which, beſides the advantage it promiſes to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, has a Penalty annex'd to the non-performance, or as an onely expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to avoid a great miſchief, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a great good.</p>
                     <p>Thus when in the <hi>Theatrum Chymicum</hi> ſome of its chief Authors, as <hi>Lully, Geber, Artephius,</hi> who pretend to have been <hi>Adepti,</hi> i. e. Poſſeſſors of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixir, very earneſtly exhort their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to apply themſelves to ſo noble and uſeful a ſtudy as <hi>Alchymy</hi> (by the help of which, the laſt nam'd <hi>Artephius</hi>
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:48436:63"/>is ſaid to have liv'd a 1000 years,) they make but a Propoſition of the firſt ſort. For though a proſperous attempt to make the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone</hi> (ſuppoſing there be ſuch a thing) would poſſeſs a Man of an ineſtimable Treaſure; yet, if he either refuſe to believe theſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or, if he do believe them, refuſes to take the pains requir'd of him that would follow their counſel, he can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſs of the wealth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they would make him hope for, but is really never a whit the poorer, or in a worſe condition than if they had not endeavour'd to engage him.</p>
                     <p>But if an abſolute Sovereign com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſomething to be done by his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and to enforce his Command, does not only propoſe great Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes to thoſe that ſhall perform what is preſcrib'd, but threatens heavy penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the diſobedient; this will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the ſecond ſort of Caſes above mention'd, in which, as 'tis evident, a Man has not the ſame latitude allow'd him as in the firſt.</p>
                     <p>But if we ſuppoſe, that a Man by a tranſlation of very peccant Matter has got a ſpreading Gangrene in his Arm, and a skilful Chirurgion tell him, that,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48436:63"/>if he will part with his Arm, he may be recover'd, and ſave his life, which elſe he will certainly loſe: This Caſe will belong to the laſt ſort above mention'd; the Patients parting with his Arm being the onely remedy of the Gangrene, and expedient to ſave his life, and recover his health. And here alſo 'tis manifeſt, that there are far ſtronger Motives, than thoſe mention'd in the firſt Caſe, to make a poſitive and timely Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>To bring this home to our Subject, I need but mind you, that the Chriſtian Doctrine does not only promiſe a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſincere Believers, but threatens no leſs than a Hell to the Refractory.</p>
                     <p>The voice of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews</hi> is this, <hi>Behold, I ſet before you this day a bleſſing and a curſe;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Deutr. 11.26, 27, 28.</note> 
                        <hi>a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, if ye obey the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord your God, which I command you this day; and a curſe, if ye will not obey the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord your God, but turn aſide out of the way which I command you this day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And the Commiſſion that Chriſt gave his Apoſtles to preach the Goſpel, runs thus: <hi>Go ye into all the world, and preach
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48436:64"/>the Goſpel to every creature,</hi> i. e. to all Mankind;
<note place="margin">Mark 16.15, 16.</note> 
                        <hi>he that believeth, and is baptiz'd ſhall be ſav'd; but he that believeth not, ſhall be damn'd.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By this you may perceive, that as far as there is either truth or probability in the Chriſtian Religion, ſo far forth he that refuſes to become a Diſciple to it, runs a venture, not only to loſe the greateſt bleſſings that Men can hope but to fall eternally into the greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that they can fear. And indeed our Caſe in reference to the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may not only be refer'd to the ſecond ſort of Caſes lately mention'd, but to the third ſort too. For as the language of the Author of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion was to his Auditors, <hi>If ye believe not that I am He</hi> (the Meſſias) <hi>ye ſhall dye in your ſins;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">John 8.24.</note> ſo of the two greateſt Heralds of it, the one tells the <hi>Jews</hi> that neither is there ſalvation in any other: For, <hi>there is no other Name under heaven given among men whereby we muſt be ſaved:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Acts 4.12.</note> And the other tells the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> That the <hi>Lord Jeſus ſhall be reveal'd from heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, taking vengeance
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:48436:64"/>on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1. 7, 8, 9.</note> 
                        <hi>who ſhall be puniſh'd with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By all this it appears, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion is not propos'd barely as a proffer of Heaven in caſe Men em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, but as a Law that Men ſhould embrace it upon the greateſt penalty, and as the onely expedient and remedy to attain eternal happineſs, and eſcape endleſs miſery; ſo that the forbearing to ſubmit our necks to the yoke of Chriſt, being as well a ruinous courſe, as to reject it, that which Reaſon here puts us upon, is, not ſo much to conſider, whether or no the Arguments for the Chriſtian Religion be Demonſtrations, and will enable a Man to anſwer directly all Objections and Scruples; (for there are divers courſes that Prudence may enjoin a Man to ſteer, whilſt Philoſophy ſuggeſts ſpeculative doubts about the grounds of ſuch Reſolutions;) but whether it be more likely to be true, than not to be true, or rather, whether it be not more adviſeable to perform the conditions it requires upon a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48436:65"/>expectation of obtaining the bleſſings it promiſes, than by refuſing it to run a probable hazard of incurring ſuch great and endleſs miſeries as it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily threatens.</p>
                     <p>It will perhaps be ſaid, that this is a hard Caſe. But that is an Allegation I am not here to conſider; ſince it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belongs to the Doctrine about the Providence of God, who being the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Author and abſolute Lord of the Creatures, who can receive neither Laws nor Benefits from them, that can oblige him to them; has a right to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them what Laws he thinks fit, that are not impoſſible for them to obey, and to puniſh their diſobedience to ſuch Laws; and much more has a right to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex what conditions he pleaſes to that ineſtimable Felicity he holds forth; the proffer of it upon any terms being a free act of his meer goodneſs, and the value of it incomparably ſurpaſſing whatever we Men can do or ſuffer to obtain it; eſpecially conſidering, that, as he might enſorce his Commands, as Sovereigns commonly do by threatning Penalties to the diſobedient, without propoſing Rewards to the performers; ſo he has given Men ſuch probable Arguments to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:48436:65"/>ground their expectations on, that they will be ſelf-condemn'd, if they reject the Religion he propoſes, and yet main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it to be decent (if I may ſo ſpeak) for him to crown their Faith with unva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable bleſſings. But, as I was ſaying, the direct and full Anſwer to this Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation belongs not to this place, where it may ſuffice to ſay, that whether the Caſe be hard or no, yet this is the Caſe. And therefore though the proofs of the Chriſtian Religion did not amount (which yet I do not grant) to Moral Demonſtrations, a Man may act ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in embracing that Religion, if, all things conſider'd, it appear more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be true, than not to be true.</p>
                     <p>And I ſhall by and by ſhew you, that this is not the onely Caſe, where Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence puts us upon making reſolutions notwithſtanding contrary doubts.</p>
                     <p>I know the harſhneſs of the Caſe is by moſt Men made to conſiſt in this, That for a Religion, whereof the truth ſuppos'd in its promiſes and threats is not demonſtratively prov'd, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign up our pleaſures, and ſometimes undergo conſiderable hardſhips and loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and conſequently we muſt quit what is certain, for what is uncertain. I have
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:48436:66"/>in another Paper had occaſion to ſay ſomething elſe to this Objection, than what (to avoid repetition) ſhall make up my preſent Anſwer, which conſiſts of two parts.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> whereof is, That what we are to give up to become Chriſtians, is not really ſo valuable in itſelf as the Objecters think, and that 'tis of ſcarce any value at all, if compar'd to the goods we may acquire by parting with them. For alas! what is it that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity requires us to forego, but ſmall petty enjoyments? which thoſe, that have had the moſt of, have found them, and pronounced them unſatisfactory whilſt they poſſeſt them, and which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt experience ſhews to be no leſs tranſitory, than they have been declar'd empty, ſince a thouſand Accidents may take them from us, and Death will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly after a ſhort time (which can be but a moment compar'd to Eternity) take us from them. And if it be ſaid, that theſe Enjoyments, ſuch as they are, are at leaſt the only happineſs that we can make our ſelves ſure of, I muſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſs, that I think it therefore the more reaſonable to part with them, if it be neceſſary upon the hopes that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:48436:66"/>Religion gives us. For (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if a Man behold thoſe things not only with a Philoſophical eye that can look <hi>through</hi> them, but with a Chriſtian eye that can look <hi>beyond</hi> them,) if there be no greater happineſs, I do not think ſo poor a thing as Men call Happineſs worth being greedily deſir'd; and if there be ſuch a tranſcendent happineſs as Chriſtianity holds forth, I am ſure, that deſerves to be the object of my Ambition. So that either the Meanneſs of worldly happineſs will make me think it no great miſery to want it, or the Excellency of heavenly Felicity will make me think it great wiſdom to part with earthly for it.</p>
                     <p>And now, in the <hi>ſecond</hi> part of my Anſwer, I muſt invite you to conſider with me, that Chriſtian Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires not of us actions more imprudent, than divers others, that are generally look'd upon as complying with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Prudence, and ſome of them practis'd by great Politicians themſelves in the weighty affairs of State.</p>
                     <p>You know what a common practice it is in great ſtorms at Sea, for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants themſelves to throw over-board their Goods, and perhaps too their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:48436:67"/>(as in <hi>Paul</hi>'s caſe) though they be ſure to loſe what they caſt away, and are not certain either that this loſs will ſave the ſhip, or that the ſhip may not be ſav'd without it. The wiſeſt, and ev'n the worldlieſt Men, whether Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or private perſons, think themſelves never more ſo, than when they toyl and lay out their care and time, and uſually deny themſelves many things to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide advantagiouſly for Children which they have but a Womans word for, and conſequently a bare Moral probability to aſſure them to be theirs.</p>
                     <p>In the <hi>Small Pox</hi> many Phyſitians are for Bleeding, and others (as moſt of our Engliſh Practitioners) are very much againſt it. Suppoſing then (which is no very rare Caſe) that a perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded by that diſeaſe, be told by one of his Phyſitians, that unleſs Nature be eas'd of part of her burden by Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy, ſhe will never be able to overcome the diſeaſe; and on the contrary, the other aſſures him, that, if by exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the treaſure of life (the Blood) he further weakens Nature which is but too weak already, the diſeaſe muſt needs overcome her: What can a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Man do in this Caſe, where he
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:48436:67"/>can take no reſolution, againſt which probable Arguments, that are not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and fully to be anſwer'd, may not be oppos'd, and where yet the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of his reſolution may be as rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, as the venturing to take either of thoſe he is invited to?</p>
                     <p>And in the formerly mentioned Caſe, of a Man that has a ſpreading Gangrene in his Arm, if he conſents that it be cut off, which Prudence often requires that he ſhould do, he is certain to loſe one of his uſefulleſt limbs, and is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain but that he may ſave his life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that loſs, nor that he ſhall ſave it by that loſs.</p>
                     <p>And to give you an Inſtance or two of a more publick nature: How many Examples does Hiſtory afford us of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Generals and other great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, who have ventur'd their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and their Lives to ſeize upon places promis'd to be betray'd to them by thoſe they had corrupted with money; though the ground, upon which they run this hazard, be the engagement of ſome, who, if they were not Traytors that could falſifie their faith, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been brib'd to make ſo crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and ignominious an engagement?
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:48436:68"/>How often have the greateſt Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans either reſolv'd to enter into a War, or taken courſes that they foreſee will end in a War, upon the informations they receive from thoſe they have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in other Princes Councils; though, to believe ſuch Intelligencers, thoſe who venture ſo much upon their informations, muſt ſuppoſe them faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and perfidious Men?</p>
                     <p>It were not difficult, to add other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to the ſame purpoſe, by which join'd with what has been above diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd, it may appear, that a Man need not renounce or lay aſide his Reaſon to reſolve to fulfill the conditions of the Goſpel, though the Arguments for it were none of them demonſtrative ones. For ſo much as a Probability of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by it ſuch ineſtimable bleſſings, as it propoſes, and little more than a bare Probability of incurring, by rejecting it, ſuch unſpeakable miſeries as it threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, may rationally induce a Man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon fulfilling its reaſonable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and his Prudence may very well be juſtifi'd if it do but appear, that (1) It is more probable that ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhould be true, than that ſo many well atteſted Miracles alledg'd by the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:48436:68"/>ancient Chriſtians ſhould be falſe; and that God who is the Author of the World, and of Men, (for ſo much, I think, may be Phyſically prov'd) ſhould leave Man whom he has ſo fitted, and by benefits and internal Laws obliged to worſhip him, without any expreſs dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction how to do it: And that (2) If there be any true Religion, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is the moſt likely to be that, in regard not only of the excellency of its Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Promiſes, but of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Miracles that bare witneſs to it, the Records of which were made by honeſt plain Men, who taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed the ſtricteſt virtue, and who knew their Religion condemn'd Lying, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly join'd their Doctrine and Narratives with their blood: the truth of which was ſo manifeſt in the times when they were ſaid to be done, that the evidence ſeem'd abundantly ſufficient to convert whole Nations, and among them many conſiderable and prudent perſons, who had great opportunity as well as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to examine the truth of them, and who were by their intereſt and educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo indiſpos'd to embrace Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that, to make a ſincere profeſſion of it, they muſt neceſſarily relinquiſh both
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:48436:69"/>their former Religion, and their former Vices, and venturouſly expoſe for it not only their Fortunes, but their Lives.</p>
                     <p>If it be here objected, that it is very harſh, if not unreaſonable, to exact up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo great penalty as Damnation ſo firm an aſſent, as is requiſite to Faith, to ſuch Doctrines as are either obſcurely delivered, or have not their truth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively made out: I anſwer, that whatever others may think, I don't be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that there is any degree of Faith abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, that is not ſutable to the evidence that Men may have of it, if they be not wanting to themſelves through Lazineſs, Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, Vice, Paſſion, Intereſt, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther culpable defect. For conſidering that God is juſt, and gracious, and has been pleas'd to promulgate the Goſpel, that Men whom it ſuppoſes to act as ſuch (that is, as rational Creatures) ſhould be brought to ſalvation by it; I ſee no juſt cauſe to think, that he intends to make any thing abſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation, that they may not ſo far clearly underſtand as they are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſtinctly and explicitely to believe it; and what is not ſo deliver'd, I ſhould, for that very Reaſon, unwillingly admit
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:48436:69"/>to be neceſſary to ſalvation: And you may here remember, that I formerly told you, I was far from thinking all the Tenents either of the Schools, or of particular Churches, to be ſo much as Chriſtian Verities, and therefore am very unlike to allow them here to be funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental and neceſſary ones; and I take it to be almoſt as great as common a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, that all the Doctrines that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern</hi> fundamental Articles, muſt <hi>be</hi> fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental too; as if becauſe the Head is a noble part of the Body, and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to life, therefore all the hair that grows upon it, muſt be thought ſuch too. But then as to the abſolute firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Aſſent, that is ſuppoſed to be exacted by Chriſtianity to the Articles it delivers, I am not ſure that 'tis ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in all caſes to true and ſaving Faith, as very many take it to be. For firſt the Scripture itſelf tells us, that ſome of the Truths it reveals, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathomable Myſteries, and ſome other Points are <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, hard to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; and 'tis unreaſonable to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the higheſt firmneſs of Aſſent is to be given to ſuch Articles, or to thoſe parts of them, as their obſcurity keeps us from having ſo much reaſon to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:48436:70"/>think that we clearly underſtand them, as we have to ſuppoſe we underſtand thoſe that are far more plainly reveal'd. And (ſecondly) to ſpeak more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, 'tis harſh to ſay, that the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Faith is neceſſary to all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſince Mens natural capacities and diſpoſitions, and their education, and the opportunities they have had of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed, do very much, yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not culpably, diſpoſe ſome more than others to be diffident, and apt to haeſitate, and frame doubts. And the ſame Arguments may appear evident e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to one Man to make it his duty to believe firmly what they perſuade, which in another, naturally more ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, or better acquainted with the difficulties and objections urged by the oppoſite Party, may leave ſome doubts and ſcruples excuſable enough. And when either the Doctrine itſelf is not clearly deliver'd, or the Proofs of it, that a Man could yet meet with, are not fully cogent; for that Man, not to give ſuch Truths the ſame degree of Aſſent that Demonſtration may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, is not, as many interpret it, an affront to the Veracity of God, ſince he may be heartily diſpoſed and ready to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:48436:70"/>believe all that ſhall appear to him to be revealed by God, and only doubts, whether the thing propoſed be indeed revealed by him, or whether the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Party rightly underſtands the ſenſe of theſe words wherein the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is contain'd; which is not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt God, but himſelf: And that in ſome caſes, a degree of Faith not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from doubts, may, through Gods goodneſs, be accepted, we may learn from hence, that the Apoſtles themſelves, who were ſo much in Chriſts favour, made it their Prayer to him, <hi>That he would encreaſe their Faith:</hi> And he that beg'd, that if he could do any thing for his ſon, and cryed out, <hi>Lord I believe, help thou my unbelief,</hi> was ſo far accepted by that merciful High Prieſt, who is apt to be toucht with the ſenſe of our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that his Requeſt was granted, though it could not be ſo but by having a Miracle done in his favor. The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples diſtreſt by a ſtorm, and crying to their Maſter, as thinking themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very point of periſhing, were ſaved by him at the ſame time when he gave them the Epithet <hi>of men of little faith:</hi> And at another time, <hi>Peter</hi> walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Sea, though he had loſt a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:48436:71"/>degree of that Faith that made him firſt engage upon that adventure, and was reproved for it by Chriſt, was yet reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from that ſinking condition which both he and his Faith were in. And we are told, in the Goſpel, of a Faith, which, though no bigger than a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, may enable a Man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move Mountains: And though this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſpeaks not primarily of juſtifying Faith, yet ſtill it may ſerve to ſhew, that degrees of Aſſent, far ſhort of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, may be ſo far accepted by God, as to be owned by miraculous Exertions of his Power. For the <hi>Faith</hi> then that is made a neceſſary condition under the Goſpel, as the genuine fruit and ſcope of it is <hi>Obedience;</hi> ſo 'tis not indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably ſuch a Faith as excludes doubts, but refuſals. And though the Aſſent be not ſo ſtrong as may be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by a Demonſtration; yet it may be graciouſly accepted, if it be but ſtrong enough to produce Obedience; and accordingly whereas <hi>Paul</hi> in one place declares, <hi>that in Chriſt Jeſus neither circumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but faith operative through love;</hi> we may learn his meaning from a paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel place, where varying the words, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:48436:71"/>not the ſenſe, of the latter part of the ſentence, he ſays, <hi>that in Chriſt Jeſus nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion but the keeping of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God.</hi> I readily grant, that attainment of a higher degree of Faith is always a bleſſing, and cannot be ſufficiently prized, without being ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely aimed at; but there are in ſome Virtues and Graces degrees, which though to reach be a great happineſs, yet 'tis but the endeavoring after them that is an indiſpenſible Duty. Likewiſe 'tis true, that the firmneſs of aſſent to Divine Verities, does, in ſome regard, bring much honour to God; as 'tis ſaid of the Father of the Faithful, (who in reference to the promiſe made him of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> did not conſider his own age, nor <hi>Sarahs</hi> long barrenneſs, ſo as to entertain any diffidence of what God had told him,) that being mighty in faith, he gave glory to God: But 'tis true too, that in another reſpect a practical aſſent built upon a leſs undoubted evidence, may have its preheminence; for when Chriſt now riſen from the dead, had ſaid to the diſtruſtful <hi>Didimus,</hi> Thomas, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt ſeen me, thou haſt believed;</hi> he
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:48436:72"/>immediately adds, <hi>But bleſſed</hi> (that is, peculiarly and preferably bleſſed) <hi>are thoſe that have not ſeen, and yet have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved;</hi> and indeed he does not a little honour God, (in that ſenſe wherein Mortals may be ſaid to honour him) who is ſo willing to obey and ſerve him, and ſo ambitious to be in an eſtate where he may always do ſo, that upon what he yet diſcerns to be but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of the Chriſtian Religions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt acceptable to God, he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces it with all its difficulties and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and upon this ſcore venturouſly reſolves to ſubmit, if need be, to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and actual dereliction of all his Sins and Luſts, and perhaps his Intereſt and his Life too, upon a comparatively uncertain expectation of living with him hereafter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:48436:72"/>
                     <head>The Concluſion of the Firſt Part.</head>
                     <p>And here I will put a Period to my Anſwer to your Friends Queſtion in one of the two ſenſes of it, and ſo to the firſt Part of this Diſcourſe. Againſt all which perhaps your Friend will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, That at this rate of arguing for the Chriſtian Religion, one may Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logize for any Opinion, and reconcile the moſt unreaſonable ones to right Reaſon. But 'tis not difficult for me to reply, That this Objection is grounded either upon a miſtake of the deſign of this Letter, or upon the overlooking of what is ſuppos'd in it. For I do not pretend, that the Conſiderations hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to alledg'd ſhould paſs for Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Truth of Chriſtianity, which is to be prov'd <hi>by</hi> the excellency of the Doctrines it teaches, and that of the Rewards it promiſes, (both which are worthy of God,) and <hi>by</hi> divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arguments, eſpecially the <hi>Divine Miracles</hi> that atteſt it: But that which I was here to do, was, not to lay down the grounds why I receiv'd the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, but to return an Anſwer, backt with Reaſons, to the Queſtion
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:48436:73"/>that was propos'd: <hi>Whether I did not think, that a Chriſtian, to continue ſuch, muſt deny or lay aſide his Reaſon?</hi> The ſum of the Anſwer is this, That the Doctrines <hi>really propos'd</hi> by the Chriſtian Religion, ſeeming to me to be by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Arguments ſufficiently prov'd in their kind, ſo as that the <hi>proofs</hi> of it, whether they be <hi>demonſtrative</hi> or no, are <hi>ſufficient,</hi> (the nature of the things to be prov'd, conſider'd) to juſtifie a rational and prudent Man's embracing it; this Religion (I ſay) ſeeming to me to have ſuch poſitive Proofs for it, I do not think, that the Objections, that are ſaid to be drawn from Reaſon againſt it, do really prove the belief of it to be inconſiſtent with right Reaſon, and do outweigh the Arguments alledgable in that Religions behalf. To propoſe ſome of the general grounds of this Anſwer of mine, was the deſign of the Conſiderations hitherto diſcours'd of; which (as I hinted to you at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) could be no other than general, unleſs you had mention'd to me ſome of your Friends particular Objections, which when he tells you, you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps find that I have already given you the grounds of anſwering them. And
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:48436:73"/>though to propoſe Arguments to evince poſitively the Truth of our Religion after the example of the excellent <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and ſome other very learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, be not, as you ſee, either my task or my deſign; yet if you attentively conſider what I write in that ſhort Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, wherein I manage but that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly popular Argument for Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that is drawn from the Miracles that are ſaid to atteſt it, you will perchance be invited to think, that when all the other Proofs of it are taken in, a Man may, without renouncing or affronting his Reaſon, be a Chriſtian.</p>
                     <p>But to proceed to the more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable part of what I preſum'd your Friend will object, I anſwer, That the conſiderations I have alledg'd in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of ſome Myſteries of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, will not be equally appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to the moſt abſurd or unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Opinions. For theſe Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are offer'd as Apologies for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Doctrines, but upon two or all of theſe three Suppoſitions. The firſt, That the Truth of the main Religion of which ſuch Doctrines make a part, is ſo far poſitively prov'd by real and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controul'd Miracles, and other compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:48436:74"/>Arguments, that nothing, but the manifeſt and irreconcileable Repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of its Doctrines to right Reaſon, ought to hinder us from believing them. The ſecond, That divers of the things, at which reaſonable Men are wont to take exception, are ſuch, as Reaſon it ſelf may diſcern to be very difficult, or perhaps impoſſible for us to underſtand perfectly by our own natural light. And the third, That ſome things in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity which many Men think contrary to Reaſon, are, at moſt, but contrary to it, as 'tis <hi>incompetently</hi> inform'd and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, but not when 'tis more fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and particularly when 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned and aſſiſted by Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as I think theſe three Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are not juſtly applicable, (I ſay not, as the Objection does, to the moſt abſurd, or unreaſonable Opinions, but,) to any other Religion than the true, which is the Chriſtian; ſo the laſt of theſe Suppoſitions prompts me to take notice to you, that, though we ought to be exceeding wary, how we admit what pretends to be ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reveal'd; yet if it be attended with ſufficient evidence of its being ſo, we do very much wrong and prejudice
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:48436:74"/>our ſelves, if out of an unreaſonable jealouſie, or, to acquire or maintain the repute of being wiſer than others, we ſhut our eyes againſt the light it offers. For beſides that a Man may as well err by rejecting or ignoring the Truth, as by miſtaking a falſhood for it; I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that thoſe Men that have an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of knowledge, which other Men either have not, or, (which is as bad) refuſe to employ, have a very great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage above others towards the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of Truth, and with far leſs parts than they, may diſcover divers things, which the others, with all their Pride and Induſtry, ſhall never attain to. As when <hi>Galilaeo</hi> alone among the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Aſtronomers was Maſter of a <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcope,</hi> 'twas eaſie for him to make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcoveries in Heaven of things, to which not only <hi>Ptolomy, Alphonſus,</hi> and <hi>Ticho,</hi> but ev'n his Maſters, <hi>Ariſtarchus Samius,</hi> and <hi>Copernicus,</hi> themſelves never dream'd of, and which other Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers cannot ſee but by making uſe of the ſame kind of Inſtrument. And on this occaſion let me carry the Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſuggeſted by the <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> a little further, and take notice, that if Men having heard, that there were four Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:48436:75"/>moving about <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and that <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> is an opacous body, and ſometimes horn'd like the Moon, had reſolv'd to examine theſe things by their naked eyes, as by the proper Organs of Sight, without employing the <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> by which they might ſuſpect, that <hi>Galilaeo</hi> might put ſome Optical deluſion upon them; they would perhaps have aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in great multitudes to gaze at <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> that (ſince <hi>plus vident Oculi quam Oculus</hi>) the number of eyes might make amends for their dimneſs. This attempt not ſucceeding, they would perhaps chooſe out ſome of the youngeſt and ſharpeſt ſighted Men, that by their piercing eyes that may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd which ordinary ones could not reach. And this Expedient not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding neither, they would perhaps diet their Stargazers, and preſcribe them the inward uſe of Fennel, and Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bright, and externally apply <hi>Collyriums</hi> and Eye-waters, and thoſe to as little purpoſe as the reſt. With ſuch a pity, mix'd with Indignation, as <hi>Galilaeo</hi> would probably have look'd on ſuch vain and fruitleſs attempts with, may a judicious Chriſtian, that upon a due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination admits the Truth of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:48436:75"/>look upon the preſumptuous and vain endeavors of thoſe Men, who, by the goodneſs of their natural parts, or by the improvements of them, or by the number of thoſe that conſpire in the ſame ſearch, think, with the bare eye of Reaſon to make as great diſcoveries of heavenly Truths, as a perſon aſſiſted by the Revelations, contain'd in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, can with great eaſe and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorineſs attain. To which let me add this further improvement of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, that <hi>as</hi> a skilful Aſtronomer will indeed firſt ſeverely examine, whether the <hi>Teleſcope</hi> be an Inſtrument fit to be truſted, and not likely to impoſe upon him; but being once reſolv'd of that, will confidently believe the diſcoveries it makes him, however contrary to the receiv'd Theories of the Celeſtial Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and to what he himſelf believ'd before, and would ſtill, if the <hi>Teleſcope</hi> did not otherwiſe inform him, continue to believe; <hi>ſo</hi> a well qualifi'd Inquirer into Religions, though he will be very wary, upon what terms he admits Scripture; yet if he once be fully ſatisfi'd, that he ought to admit it, he will not ſcruple to receive upon its authority whatever ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Truths it clearly diſcloſes to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:48436:76"/>him; though perhaps contrary to the Opinions he formerly held, and which, if the Scripture did not teach him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, he would yet aſſent to. And <hi>as</hi> the <hi>Galaxy</hi> and other whitiſh parts of the Sky, were by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and many other Philoſophers, who look'd on them only with their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked eyes, for many Ages reputed to be but Meteors; but to thoſe that look on them with an eye aſſiſted by the <hi>Teleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope,</hi> they plainly appear true Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made up of a multitude of bright (though little) Stars; <hi>ſo</hi> there are Theological Doctrines, which to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, and others that look on them with the naked eye of Natural Reaſon, ſeem to be but light and fantaſtical things; which yet, when Reaſon, aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and heightned by Revelation, comes to contemplate, it manifeſtly ſees them to be true and celeſtial Lights, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their ſublimity keeps conceal'd from our weak (naked) eyes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48436:76"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48436:77"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48436:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>SOME Phyſico-Theological <hi>CONSIDERATIONS</hi> ABOUT THE POSSIBILITY OF THE Reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>By the Honourable <hi>ROBERT BOYLE</hi> Eſq; Fellow of the Royal Society.</p>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <bibl>Angelus Gabriel, <hi>Luc. I. 37.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>H. Herringman,</hi> at the <hi>Anchor</hi> in the <hi>Lower Walk</hi> of the <hi>New Exchange.</hi> 1675.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48436:78"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48436:78"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                  <p>WHil'st the Conſiderations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> (to which the following Eſſay is annex'd) were not yet come from the Preſs, the Learned Publiſher of them falling one day into Diſcourſe with me about the Deſign they aim'd at, and ſome of the Points they treated of, and particularly the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> our Diſcourſe occaſion'd my letting him know, that I had long ſince had thoughts, and perhaps imparted ſome of them to my Friends, about ſuch Subjects; and that in particular about the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> I had yet by me a Manuſcript, wherein divers years ago I had endeavour'd to ſhew, that the Philoſophical Difficulties, urg'd againſt the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> were nothing near ſo inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as they are by ſome pretended,
<pb facs="tcp:48436:79"/>and by others granted to be. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Notice, the Curioſity he expreſs'd to ſee this Eſſay, engaged me quickly to bring it him; though my being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to go from <hi>London</hi> made me do it without ſtaying to look it over my ſelf; much leſs to add what ſince oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd to me about the things treated of in it. But notwithſtanding its Imperfections, and my unwillingneſs to let it go abroad; eſpecially with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome Papers that ſhould have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded it, the Learned Peruſer <hi>would not</hi> be denied leave to ſend it, (in my abſence) unalter'd to the Preſs, and join it to the Tract he expected thence; poſitively affirming, that I ought no longer to ſtifle a Diſcourſe, that he judg'd very ſeaſonable, and thought likely to do good. In which Conjecture if he do not prove miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, I hope ſome more ingenious than religious Men, ſeeing what can be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſaid by ſo incompetent a Pen as
<pb facs="tcp:48436:79"/>mine, for one of the moſt oppoſed Doctrines of Chriſtianity, will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be made leſs forward to condemn all thoſe for Deſertors of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that ſubmit to <hi>Revelation.</hi> And I ſhall hope too, (on the other ſide,) that ſome more Religious, than, in this matter, well-inform'd Men, will be induc'd to think, that what they call the <hi>New Philoſophy</hi> may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us with ſome new Weapons for the defence of our ancienteſt <hi>Creed;</hi> and that <hi>Corpuſcularian</hi> Principles may not only be admitted <hi>without</hi> Epicurean Errors, but be employ'd <hi>againſt</hi> them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48436:80"/>
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>PAg. 3. line 26. read <hi>deceaſe</hi> for <hi>decreaſe.</hi> p. 10. l. 21. read <hi>Kircherus, a Polonian Phyſitian in Querceta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> p. 12. l. 36. r. <hi>require.</hi> p. 13. l. 27. r. <hi>is meant.</hi> p. 15. l. penult. read <hi>firſt poſſeſſor.</hi> p. 17. l. 1. r. <hi>are of a.</hi> p. 29. l. 4. r. <hi>I did (purpoſely) but touch.</hi> p. 39. l. 7. r. <hi>and</hi> for <hi>an.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48436:80"/>
                  <head>Some Phyſico-Theological <hi>CONSIDERATIONS</hi> ABOUT The POSSIBILITY OF THE RESURRECTION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queſtion about which my thoughts are deſired being this; <hi>Whether to believe the Reſurrection of the Dead, which the Chriſtian Religion teaches, be not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve an Impoſſibility?</hi> I ſhall, before I proceed any further, crave leave to ſtate the Queſtion ſomewhat more clearly and diſtinctly; that, being freed from Ambiguities, you may the better know in what ſenſe I underſtand it in my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; in the returning whereof, your Friend need not deſire me to inſiſt but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48436:81"/>upon my own Thoughts, unleſs he could do me the favor to direct me to ſome Author, which I have not yet ſeen, that has expreſly treated, upon Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal grounds, of the Queſtion he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then I take it for granted, that he does not mean, whether the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> is a thing knowable, or directly provable by the meer Light of Nature. For, if God had not, in the Scripture, poſitively revealed his purpoſe of Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Dead, I confeſs, I ſhould not have thought of any ſuch thing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I know, how to prove that it will be, but by flying, not only, to the Veracity, but the Power of God; who having declar'd that he will raiſe the Dead, and being an Almighty Agent, I have reaſon to believe, that he will not fail to perform what he has foretold.</p>
                  <p>Nor do I (ſecondly) underſtand the Queſtion to be, Whether the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> be poſſible to be effected by meerly Phyſical Agents and means. For that it is not to be brought to paſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I preſume; after the univerſal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of ſo many Ages, which have afforded us no inſtances of it. And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48436:81"/>though perhaps in Speculation it ſeems not abſolutely repugnant to Reaſon, that the ſcatter'd parts of a dead Body might be reconjoin'd, ſoon after the death of the Man; yet I think you will eaſily grant it to be morally impoſſible, that this ſhould happen to any one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and much more, that it may, nay, that it will, happen to all the perſons of Mankind at the worlds end: So that when I treat of the poſſibility of the <hi>General Reſurrection,</hi> I take it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that God has been pleas'd to promiſe and declare, that there ſhall be one, and that it ſhall be effected, not by or accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ordinary courſe of Nature, but by his own Power. On which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, I remember, that when our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, treating of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> ſilenc'd the <hi>Sadduces</hi> that deny'd it, he conjoins, as the cauſes of their Error, the two things I have pointed at in this Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the firſt that preceded it: <hi>You err,</hi> ſays he, <hi>not knowing the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, nor the Power of God.</hi> And when an Angel would aſſure the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, that ſhe ſhould bare a Child with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the intervention of a Man, (which was a caſe ſomewhat akin to ours, ſince 'twas a production of a Humane Body
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48436:82"/>out of a ſmall portion of humane ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in a ſupernatural way,) he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes his ſpeech by telling her, <hi>That nothing ſhall prove impoſſible to God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the third place, I ſuppoſe, that the Article of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> taught by the Chriſtian Religion, is not here meant by the Propoſer in ſuch a lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as to comprize all that any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church or Sect of Chriſtians, much leſs any private Doctor or other Writer, hath taught about the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> but only what is <hi>plainly</hi> taught about it in the holy Scriptures themſelves. And therefore, if beſides what is there ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd, the Propoſer hath met with any thing that he judges to be impoſſible in its own Nature, he hath my free conſent to deal with the Authors and Abettors of ſuch unreaſonable Opinions, (which I declare my ſelf to be not only uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to defend, but ſufficiently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to reject,) as raſhneſſes unfriend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the growth of Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And now, that I may yet further clear the way for the Diſcourſe that is to follow, and obviate ſome Objections and Scruples, which I think 'tis better ſeaſonably to prevent, than ſolemnly to anſwer; I ſhall deſire your leave to lay
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48436:82"/>down in this place a couple of Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations; of which I ſhall begin with this, that 'tis no ſuch eaſie way, as at firſt it ſeems, to determine what is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary and but ſufficient to make a portion of Matter, conſider'd at dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering times or places, to be fit to be reputed the <hi>ſame</hi> Body.</p>
                  <p>That the generality of Men do in vulgar Speech allow themſelves a great latitude about this affair, will be eaſily granted by him, that obſerves the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived forms of ſpeaking. Thus <hi>Rome</hi> is ſaid to be the <hi>ſame</hi> City, though it hath been ſo often taken and ruin'd by the Barbarians and others, that perhaps ſcarce any of the firſt houſes have been left ſtanding, and at leaſt very few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in compariſon of thoſe that have been demoliſhed, and have had others built in their ſtead. Thus an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is ſaid to be the <hi>ſame,</hi> though ſome Colledges fall to ruine, and new ones are built; and though once in an Age all the perſons that compos'd it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and are ſucceeded by others. Thus the <hi>Thames</hi> is ſaid to be the <hi>ſame</hi> River, that it was in the time of our Forefathers, though indeed the water that now runs under <hi>London-bridge,</hi> is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48436:83"/>
                     <hi>not the ſame</hi> that ran there an hour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, and is quite other than that which will run there an hour hence. And ſo the <hi>Flame</hi> of a Candle is ſaid to be the ſame for many hours together, though it indeed be every minute a new body, and the kindled Particles, that compoſe it at any time aſſign'd, are continually putting off the form of flame, and are repaired by a ſucceſſion of like ones.</p>
                  <p>Nor is it by the Vulgar only that the Notion of <hi>Identity</hi> has been uneaſie to be penetrated. For it ſeems, that even the ancient Philoſophers have been puzled about it, witneſs their Diſputes, whether the ſhip of <hi>Theſeus</hi> were the <hi>ſame</hi> after it had (like that of Sir <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Drake)</hi> been ſo patch'd up from time to time to preſerve it as a Monument, that ſcarce any Plank remain'd of the former ſhip, new Timber having been ſubſtituted in the place of any part that in length of time rotted. And even in <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi> themſelves, I think it no eaſie task to eſtabliſh a true and ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Notion of <hi>Identity,</hi> and clearly determine, what is the true Principle of <hi>Individuation.</hi> And at all this I do not much wonder; for almoſt every Man that thinks, conceives in his mind
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48436:83"/>this or that Quality or Relation, or Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate of Qualities, to be that which is eſſential to ſuch a Body, and proper to give it ſuch a Denomination; whereby it comes to paſs, that, as one Man chiefly reſpects this thing, and another that, in a Body that bears ſuch a name; ſo one Man may eaſily look upon a Body as the <hi>ſame,</hi> becauſe it retains what he chiefly conſider'd in it, whilſt another thinks it to be chang'd into a new Body, becauſe it has loſt that which <hi>he</hi> thought was the denominating Quality or Attribute. Thus Philoſophers and Phyſitians diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree about <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Ice,</hi> ſome taking the latter to be but the former diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe they are both of them cold and ſimple Bodies, and the latter eaſily reducible to the former, by being freed from the exceſſive and adventitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of coldneſs; whil'ſt others, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon fluidity as eſſential to Water, think Ice upon the ſcore of its ſolidity to be a diſtinct <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Bodies. And ſo <hi>Peripateticks</hi> and <hi>Chymiſts</hi> often diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree about the Aſhes and <hi>Calces</hi> of burnt Bodies; the firſt referring them to Earth, becauſe of their permanency and fixtneſs, and divers of the <hi>Spagyriſts</hi> taking them to be Bodies <hi>ſui generis,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48436:84"/>becauſe common Aſhes uſually contain a cauſtick Salt, whereas Earth ought to be inſipid: And the like may be ſaid of ſome Wood-aſhes and Lime-ſtone, and even Coral, which, when well-calcin'd and recent, have a biting taſte, beſides that ſome of them that are inſipid may be reduc'd into Metals, as may be eaſily enough try'd in the <hi>Calces</hi> of Lead and Copper.</p>
                  <p>Theſe difficulties about the Notion of <hi>Identity</hi> I have therefore taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, that we may not think it ſtrange, that among the ancient <hi>Hebrews</hi> and <hi>Greeks,</hi> whoſe Languages were ſo remote in ſeveral regards from ours, the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar expreſſions employ'd about the <hi>ſameneſs</hi> of a Body ſhould not be ſo preciſe as were requiſite for <hi>their</hi> turn, who maintain the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> in the moſt rigid ſenſe. And this leads me from the firſt of my two Conſiderations to the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>That (then) 'tis not repugnant or unconſonant to the Holy Scripture, to ſuppoſe, that a comparatively ſmall quantity of the matter of a Body, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing increas'd either by Aſſimilation or other convenient-Appoſition of aptly diſpoſed matter, may bear the name of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48436:84"/>the former Body, I think I may reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly gather from the three following Expreſſions, I meet with in the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>For firſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 15th <hi>Chapter</hi> of his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where he profeſſedly treats of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> and anſwers this Queſtion; <hi>But ſome Man will ſay, How are the Dead raiſed up? And with what Body do they come?</hi> ver. 35: He more than once ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains the matter by the ſimilitude of <hi>Sowing,</hi> and tells them, <hi>Ver.</hi> 37. <hi>That which thou ſoweſt, thou ſoweſt not that Body that ſhall be; but bare Grain, it may chance of Wheat, or of ſome other Grain.</hi> Adding, <hi>that God gives this ſeed a Body as he thought fit, to each ſeed its own Body,</hi> ver. 38. Now, if we conſider the multitude of Grains of Corn, that may in a good Soil grow out of One; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that our Saviour ſpeaking in the Parable <hi>de Agro Dominico,</hi> of a whole Field, tells us, that the Grain may well bear a hundred for one: We cannot but think, that the Portion of the matter of the Seed that is in each of the Grains (not to reckon what may be contained in the Roots, Stalk, and Chaff,) muſt be very ſmall.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48436:85"/>
                  <p>I will not now conſider, whether this Text juſtifies the ſuppoſition of a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Power in ſome part of the matter of a deceaſed Body; whereby, being divinely excited, it may be enabled to take to its ſelf freſh matter, and ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due and faſhion it, as thence ſufficiently to repair or augment itſelf; though the Compariſon ſeveral times employed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſeems to favour ſuch an <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis.</hi> Nor will I examine, what may be argued from conſidering, that <hi>Leaven,</hi> though at firſt not differing from other Dough, is by a light change of Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that it acquires by time, enabled to work upon and ferment a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a great Proportion of other Dough. Nor yet will I here debate, what may be ſaid in favour of this Conjecture from thoſe Chymical Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, by which <hi>Kircherus, Querce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> and others, are affirmed to have by a gentle heat been able to repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in well-cloſed Vials the perfect Idea's of Plants deſtroyed by the fire: I will not, I ſay, in this place enter upon a Diſquiſition of any of theſe things, both becauſe I want time to go thorow with it; and becauſe, though the Reſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation, ſuppoſing the matter of Fact,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48436:85"/>may give no ſmall countenance to our Cauſe; yet I do not either abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly need it, or perhaps fully acquieſce in all the Circumſtances and Inferences that ſeem to belong to it. But one thing there is, that I muſt not leave unmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd in this place; becauſe I received it, ſoon after the Tryal was made, from two eminent Perſons of my Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Men of great Veracity as well as Judgment; whereof one made the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, and the other ſaw it made in his own Garden, where the Tryer of the Experiment, (for he was ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, that he would not confeſs himſelf to be the Author of it,) took ſome Aſhes of a Plant juſt like our Engliſh red Poppy, and having ſow'd theſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caliſate Aſhes in my Friends Garden, they did, ſooner than was expected, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce certain Plants larger and fairer than any of that kind that had been ſeen in thoſe parts. Which ſeems to argue, that in the ſaline and earthy, <hi>i. e.</hi> the fix'd Particles of a Vegetable, that has been diſſipated and deſtroyed by the violence of the fire, there may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main a Plaſtick Power inabling them to contrive diſpoſed Matter, ſo as to repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch a Body as was formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48436:86"/>But to this Plaſtick Power, reſiding in any portion of the deſtroyed Body itſelf, it will not perhaps be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to have recourſe; ſince an Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Omnipotent Agent can without it perform all that I need contend for: As I think I might gather from that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſſion of Holy Scripture, that I meet with in the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> where 'tis ſaid, <hi>That the Lord God cauſed a deep ſleep to fall upon</hi> Adam, <hi>and he ſlept; and he took one of his Ribs, and cloſed up the fleſh inſtead thereof. And the Rib which the Lord God had taken from Man, made he a Woman, and brought her unto the Man, Ver.</hi> 21, 22. For, ſince it cannot be pretended, that either the whole or any conſiderable portion of <hi>Eve</hi>'s Body was taken out of <hi>Adams,</hi> which was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but of a Rib: And ſince it cannot be probably affirm'd, that this Rib had any Spermatick Faculty, both becauſe the Text aſſigns the Formation of the Woman to God, and becauſe the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Principles in Animals requires the commixture of Male and Female, the latter of which the Text ſuppoſes not to have been then made; Why may I not conclude, That, if it pleaſe God by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48436:86"/>his immediate Operation to take a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Matter of a Humane Body, and add to it a far greater quantity, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of newly created, or of pre-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtent, Matter; the new Body ſo framed may, congruouſly enough to Scripture-expreſſions, be reputed to be made of the former Body. And accordingly <hi>Adam (Ver.</hi> 23.) gives the reaſon why he called his Wife <hi>Iſha,</hi> which our Tranſlation renders, <hi>Woman;</hi> becauſe ſhe was taken out of <hi>Iſh,</hi> which in our Verſion is render'd, <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other Text that I conſider to my preſent purpoſe, is the myſtical <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> deſcrib'd in <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Viſion, where all, that remain of the dead Men that were to riſe up an Army of living Men, was a Valley full of dry Bones, which being by the Divine Power ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd to one another, and made to join together in a convenient manner, were afterwards by the ſupernatural Appoſition of either newly created, or extrinſecally ſupplied, Matter,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 37.</note> furniſh'd with Sinews, (by which I ſuppoſe it meant not only Nerves, but Veſſels, Tendons,
<note place="margin">Ver. 7, 8.</note> Ligaments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and Fleſh cover'd with skins; and laſt of all a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48436:87"/>vivifying ſpirit was convey'd into them that made them ſtand upon their feet alive,
<note place="margin">Ver. 9, 10.</note> an exceeding great Army. Whence I gather, that 'tis not unconſonant to the expreſſions of Scripture, to ſay, that a Portion of the Matter of a dead Body, being uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a far greater Portion of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter furniſh'd from without by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and completed into a Humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, may be reputed the <hi>ſame</hi> Man that was dead before. Which may appear both by the tenor of the Viſion, and particularly from the expreſſion ſet down in the 10th verſe, where God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for the enlivening Spirit, names the completed, but not yet revived, Bodies, <hi>Theſe ſlain,</hi> as if he now counted them the ſame, that had formerly been <hi>kill'd,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe preliminary Conſiderations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus laid down, we may now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to examine more cloſely thoſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, which are ſaid to demonſtrate the <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> of the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> the ſubſtance of which difficulties may be compriz'd in this Objection.</p>
                  <p>When a man is once really dead, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the parts of his Body will, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courſe of Nature, reſolve themſelves into multitudes of ſteams
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48436:87"/>that wander to and fro in the Air; and the remaining parts, that are either li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid or ſoft, undergo ſo great a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and change, that 'tis not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo many ſcatter'd parts ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain brought together, and reunited af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner wherein they exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a humane Body, whil'ſt it was yet alive. And much more impoſſible 'tis to effect this Reunion, if the Body have been, as it often happens, devoured by wild Beaſts or Fiſhes; ſince in this caſe, though the ſcatter'd Particles of the <hi>Cadaver</hi> might be recover'd as Particles of Matter, yet having already paſt into the ſubſtance of other Animals, they are quite tranſmuted, as being informed by the new form of the Beaſt or Fiſh that devoured them, and of which they now make a Subſtantial part.</p>
                  <p>And yet far more impoſſible will this Redintegration be, if we put the caſe, that the dead Body be devoured by <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibals;</hi> for then the ſame Fleſh belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſucceſſively to two differing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, 'tis impoſſible that both ſhould have it reſtored to them at once, or that any footſteps ſhould remain of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation it had to the firſt Profeſſor.</p>
                  <p>In anſwer to this (indeed weighty)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48436:88"/>Objection, I have ſeveral things to offer.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>firſt,</hi> I conſider, that a Humane Body is not as a Statue of Braſs or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that may continue; as to ſenſe, whole ages in a permanent ſtate; but is in a perpetual flux or changing conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince it grows in all its Parts, and all its Dimenſions, from a <hi>Corpuſculum,</hi> no bigger than an Inſect, to the full ſtature of Man; which in many perſons, that are tall and fat, may amount to a vaſt bulk, which could not happen but by a conſtant appoſition and aſſimilation of new Parts to the primitive ones of the little <hi>Embryo;</hi> and ſince Men, as other Animals, grow but to a certain pitch, and till a certain age (unleſs perhaps it be the Crocodile, which ſome affirm to grow always till death,) and therefore muſt diſcharge a great part of what they eat and drink by inſenſible tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration, which <hi>Sanctorius</hi>'s Statical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, as well as mine, aſſure me to be ſcarce credibly great, as to Men and ſome other Animals, both hot and cold; it will follow, that in no very great compaſs of time, a great part of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a Humane Body muſt be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: And yet 'tis conſiderable, that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48436:88"/>of a ſtable and laſting Texture, as I found not only by ſome Chymical Tryals, but by the Sculls and Bones of men, whom Hiſtory records to have been kill'd an exeeding long time ago, of which Note we may hereafter make uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> I conſider, that there is no determinate Bulk or Size that is neceſſary to make a humane Body paſs for the ſame, and that a very ſmall portion of Matter will ſome times ſerve the turn; as an <hi>Embryo,</hi> for inſtance, in the Womb, a new born Babe, a Man at his full ſtature, and a decrepit Man of perhaps an hundred years old, notwithſtanding the vaſt difference of their ſizes, are ſtill reputed to be the ſame perſon; as is evident by the cuſtom of Crowning Kings and Emperors in the Mothers belly, and by putting Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers <hi>&amp;c</hi> to death in their old age for Crimes committed in their youth; and if a very tall and unweildy fat Man ſhould, as it ſometimes happens, be reduced by a Conſumption to a Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton, as they ſpeak, yet none would deny, that this waſted Man were the ſame with him that had once ſo enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly big a Body.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48436:89"/>
                  <p>I conſider alſo, that a Body may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſiſt of, or abound with, ſuch Corpuſcles, as may be variouſly aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with thoſe of other Bodies, and exceedingly diſguiſed with thoſe Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and yet retain their own Nature; of this we have divers inſtances in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline Bodies: Thus <hi>Gold,</hi> for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when diſſolved in <hi>Aqua Regis,</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for a Liquor, and when dexterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coagulated, it appears a Salt or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol: By another operation, I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken pleaſure to make it part of the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el of a Flame: Being dexterouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined to another Mineral, it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to Glaſs: Being well precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <hi>Mercury,</hi> it makes a glorious tranſparent Powder: Being precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Spirit of Urine, or Oyl of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar <hi>per deliquium,</hi> it makes a fulminating <hi>Calx</hi> that goes off very eaſily, yet is far ſtronger than Gun-powder: Being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated with a certain other <hi>Alkali,</hi> the Fire turns it to a fixt and purple <hi>Calx.</hi> And yet in ſpight of all theſe and divers other diſguiſes, the <hi>Gold</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains its Nature; as may be evinced by Chymical operations, eſpecially by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions. <hi>Mercury</hi> alſo is a greater <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus</hi> than Gold, ſometimes putting on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48436:89"/>the form of a Vapor; ſometimes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in that of an almoſt inſipid wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; ſometimes aſſuming in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the form of a red Pouder; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that of a white one, and of a yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one, or of a Chryſtalline Salt, of a Malleable Metal; of what not? And yet all theſe are various dreſſes of the ſame Quickſilver, which a skilful Artiſt may eaſily make it put off, and re-appear in its native ſhape.</p>
                  <p>And though it be true, that inſtances of the permanence of Corpuſcles, that paſs under ſucceſſive diſguiſes, may be much eaſier found among Metals and Minerals, than Vegetables and Animals; yet there are ſome to be met with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe: For, not to mention <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> his affirmation about purging a Child with the Milk of an Animal that had taken <hi>Elaterium,</hi> (if I miſremember not the Drugg,) not to mention this, I ſay; I remember, that when I once paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Spring in <hi>Savoy,</hi> I obſerved, that all the Butter that was made in ſome places, taſted ſo rank of a certain weed, that at that time of the year abounds there in the Fields, that it made ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers much nauſeate the Butter, which otherwiſe was very good. If it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48436:90"/>how many, if I may ſo call them, Elaborate Alterations the rank Corpuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of this weed muſt have undergone in the various digeſtions of the Cows Stomach, Heart, Breaſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that afterward two Separations at leaſt were ſuperadded, the one of the Cream from the reſt of the Milk, and the other of the unctuous parts of the Cream from the <hi>Serum</hi> or Butter-milk; it will ſcarce be deny'd, but that vegetable Corpuſcles may by aſſociation paſs through divers diſguiſes, without loſing their Nature; eſpecially conſidering, that the eſſential Attributes of ſuch Corpuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles may remain undeſtroyed, though no ſenſible quality ſurvive to make proof of it; as in our newly mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Example the offenſive Taſte did. And beſides what we commonly obſerve on the Sea-coaſt, of the Fiſhy taſte of thoſe Sea-birds, that feed onely upon Sea-fiſh, I have purpoſely enquired of an obſerving Man that lived upon a part of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Coaſt, where the Cuſtom is to fatten their Hogs with a Shell-fiſh, which that place very much abounds with, about the taſte of their Pork: To which he anſwered me, that the Fleſh had ſo ſtrong and rank a taſte
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48436:90"/>of the Fiſh, that ſtrangers could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to eat it. There is a certain fruit in <hi>America,</hi> very well known to our Engliſh Planters, which many of them call the <hi>Prickle-Peare,</hi> whoſe very red juyce being eaten with the pulp of the fruit, whereof it is a part, doth ſo well make its way through the divers ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and digeſtions of the Body, that it makes the Urine red enough to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade thoſe that are unacquainted with this property, that they piſs Blood; as I have been ſeveral times aſſured by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſpected Eye-witneſſes. But more odd is that which is related by a Learned Man, that ſpent ſeveral years upon the Dutch and Engliſh Plantations in the <hi>Charibe Iſlands,</hi> who ſpeaking of a Fruit, (which I remember I have ſeen, but had not the liberty to make tryal of it,) called <hi>Janipa,</hi> or <hi>Junipa,</hi> growing in ſeveral of thoſe Iſlands, he tells us, among other things, that <hi>au temps,</hi> &amp;c. which is at the ſeaſon when this Fruit falls from the Tree, the Hogs that feed on it, have both their Fleſh and Fat of a violet colour, as Experience witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, (which colour is the ſame that the juyce dyes;) and the like happens to the Fleſh of Parrots and other Birds
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48436:91"/>that feed upon it. I ſhall by and by give you an inſtance of a Vegetable ſubſtance, which, though torn in pieces by very corroſive Liquors, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed as to leave no ſuſpition of what it was, does thereby not only not loſe its Nature, but is in an immediate capacity of re-appearing cloathed even with the ſenſible qualities of it, as colour, taſte and ſmell.</p>
                  <p>Having thus ſhewn, that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of a Body may retain their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture under various diſguiſes, I now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to add, that they may be ſtript of thoſe diſguiſes, or, to ſpeak without a Metaphor, be extricated from thoſe Compoſitions wherein they are diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that ſometimes by ſuch ways as thoſe that are ſtrangers to the nicer operations of Nature, would never have thought upon, nor will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps judge probable when propos'd. 'Tis not unknown to expert Chymiſts, that, in deſpight of all the various ſhapes, which that <hi>Proteus, Mercury,</hi> may be made to appear in, as of a Chriſtalline Sublimate, a red Precipitate, a yellow Turbith, a Vapor, a clear Water, a Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naber, <hi/> a skilful method of Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction will quickly free it from all that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48436:91"/>made it impoſe upon our ſenſes, and reappear in the form of plain running <hi>Mercury.</hi> And though <hi>Vitrification</hi> be looked upon by Chymiſts as the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate action of the Fire, and powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt way of making inſeparable conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Bodies; yet even out of glaſs of Lead, for inſtance, (made of Sand, and the aſhes of a Metal,) though the Tranſmutation ſeems ſo great, that the dark and flexible Metal is turned into a very tranſparent and brittle maſs; yet even from this have we recover'd opa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous and malleable Lead. And though there be ſeveral ways, beſides Precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, of divorcing ſubſtances that ſeem very ſtrictly, if not unſeparably, united; (which though I may perhaps have practiſed, it is not now convenient I ſhould diſcourſe of;) yet by Precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alone, if a Man have the skill to chooſe proper Precipitants, ſeveral Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations may not only be made, but be eaſily and throughly made that every one would not think of: For, 'tis not neceſſary, that in all Precipitations, as is obſerved in moſt of the vulgar ones, the precipitant Body ſhould indeed make a Separation of the diſſolved Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from the maſs or bulk of that Liquor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48436:92"/>or other Adjunct, whereto 'twas before united, but ſhould not be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this without aſſociating its own Corpuſcles with thoſe of the Body it ſhould reſcue, and ſo make in ſome ſenſe a new and further Compoſition. For, that ſome Bodies may precipitate others without uniting themſelves with them, is eaſily proved by the Experiment of Refiners, ſeparating Silver from Copper; for, the Mixture being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> if the Solution be afterward diluted by adding fifteen or twenty times as much common water, and you put into this Liquor a Copper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, you ſhall quickly ſee the Silver begin to adhere to the Plate, not in the form of a <hi>Calx,</hi> as when Gold is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated to make <hi>Aurum fulminans,</hi> or Tin-glaſs to make a fine white Powder for a <hi>Fucus;</hi> but in the form of a ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Metalline ſubſtance that needs no farther reduction to be employed as good Silver. And by a proper Precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, I remember, I have alſo in a trice (perhaps in a minute of an hour) redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a pretty quantity of well diſguiſed <hi>Mercury</hi> into running Quickſilver. And if one can well appropriate the Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitants to the Bodies they are to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48436:92"/>very ſlight and unpromiſing Agents may perform great matters in a ſhort time; as you may gueſs by the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I lately promiſed you: Which is this, that, if you take a piece of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire,</hi> and let it lie awhile upon Oyl of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> ſhaking them now and then, it will be ſo corroded by the Oyl, as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally to diſappear therein without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſo much as its ſmell, or any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt quality, whereby one may ſuſpect there is <hi>Camphire</hi> in that Mixture; and yet, that a Vegetable ſubſtance, thus ſwallowed up, and changed by one of the moſt fretting and deſtroying ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that is yet known in the world, ſhould not only retain the eſſential qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of its Nature, but be reſtorable to its obvious and ſenſible ones, in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, and that by ſo unpromiſing a <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> as common water, you will readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grant, if you pour the diſſolved <hi>Camphire</hi> into a large proportion of that Liquor, to whoſe upper parts it will immediately emerge white, brittle, ſtrong-ſcented, and inflameable <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire,</hi> as before.</p>
                  <p>One main Conſideration I muſt add to the foregoing ones, namely, that Body and Body being but a parcel,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48436:93"/>and a parcel of univerſal Matter Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanically different; either parcel may ſucceſſively put on forms in a way of Circulation, if I may ſo ſpeak, till it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the form whence the reckoning was begun, having only its Mechanical affections alter'd.</p>
                  <p>That all Bodies agree in one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Matter, the <hi>Schools</hi> themſelves teach, making what they call the <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Prima</hi> to be the common <hi>Baſis</hi> of them all, and their ſpecifick differences to ſpring from their particular forms: And ſince the true Notion of Body conſiſts either alone in its Extenſion, or in that, and Impenetrability together it will follow, that the differences, which make the varieties of Bodies we ſee, muſt not proceed from the Nature of Matter, of which as ſuch we have but one uniform Conception; but from cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Attributes, ſuch as <hi>Motion, Size, Poſition,</hi> &amp;c. that we are wont to call Mechanical Affections. To this 'twill be congruous, that a determinate porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Matter being given, if we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that an intelligent and otherwiſe duly qualified Agent do watch this por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Matter in its whole progreſs, through the various forms it is made to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48436:93"/>put on, till it come to the end of its courſe or ſeries of changes; if, I ſay, we ſuppoſe this, and withal, that this intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Agent lay hold of this portion of Matter cloath'd in its ultimate form, and extricating it from any other parcels of Matter wherewith it may be mingled, make it exchange its laſt Mechanical Affections for thoſe which it had when the Agent firſt began to watch it; in ſuch caſe, I ſay, this portion of Matter, how many changes and diſguiſes ſoever it may have undergone in the mean time, will return to be what it was; and if it were before part of another Body to be reproduced, it will become capable of having the ſame Relation to it that formerly it had.</p>
                  <p>To explain my meaning by a groſs Example; ſuppoſe, a Man cut a large Globe or Sphere of ſoft Wax in two equal Parts or Hemiſpheres, and of the one make Cones, Cylinders, Rings, Screws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and kneading the other with Dough, make an appearance of Pie-cruſt, Cakes, Vermicell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Italians</hi> call Paſte ſqueezed through a perforated Plate into the form of little Worms,) Wafers, Biskets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'tis plain, that a Man may by diſſolution,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48436:94"/>and other ways, ſeparate the Wax from the Dough or Paſte, and reduce it in a Mould to the ſelf-ſame Hemiſphere of Wax it was before, and ſo he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all that made the other part of the Wax paſs for ſeveral Bodies, as Cones, or Cylinders, or Rings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and may reduce it in a Mould to one diſtinct Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi-globe, fit to be reconjoined to the other, and ſo to recompoſe ſuch a Sphere of Wax as they conſtituted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Biſection was made. And to give you an Example to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in a caſe that ſeems much more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult; if you look upon Precipitate, carefully made <hi>per ſe,</hi> you would think, that Art has made a Body extreamly different from the common <hi>Mercury;</hi> this being conſiſtent like a Powder, very red in colour, and purgative, and for the moſt part vomitive in operation, though you give but four or five grains of it, and yet if you but preſs this Pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with a due heat, by putting the component Particles into a new and fit motion, you may reunite them together ſo as to re-obtain or re-produce the ſame running <hi>Mercury</hi> you had, before the Precipitate <hi>per ſe</hi> was made of it.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48436:94"/>
                  <p>Here I muſt beg your leave to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend more fully to your thoughts, that which ſoon after the beginning of this Diſcourſe, I did but (purpoſely) touch upon, and invite you to conſider with me, that the Chriſtian Doctrine doth not aſcribe the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> to <hi>Nature,</hi> or any created Agent, but to the peculiar and immediate operation of <hi>God,</hi> who has declar'd, that before the very laſt judgment, he will raiſe the dead. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when I lately mentioned ſome Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical ways of recovering Bodies from their various diſguiſes, I was far from any deſire it ſhould be imagined, that ſuch ways were the only or the beſt that can poſſibly be employed to ſuch an end. For, as the generality of Men, without excepting Philoſophers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, would not have believed or thought, that, by eaſie Chymical ways, Bodies that are reputed to have paſs'd into a quite other nature, ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd or reſtor'd to their former condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo, till Chymiſtry and other parts of true Natural Philoſophy be more throughly underſtood and farther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, 'tis probable, that we can ſcarce now imagine, what Expedients to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>produce Bodies a further diſcovery of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48436:95"/>the Myſteries of Art and Nature, may lead us Mortals to. And much leſs can our dim and narrow knowledge deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, what means, even <hi>Phyſical</hi> ones, the moſt wiſe Author of Nature, and abſolute Governor of the World is able to employ to bring the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> to paſs, ſince 'tis a part of the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of inferior Natures to have but an imperfect apprehenſion of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of one that is incomparably ſuperior to them. And even among us, a <hi>Child,</hi> though indowed with a reaſonable Soul, cannot conceive, how a <hi>Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> can meaſure inacceſſible heights and diſtances, and much leſs how a Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mographer can determine the whole compaſs of the Earth and Sea, or an Aſtronomer inveſtigate how far 'tis from hence to the Moon, and tell many years before, what day and hour, and to what degree, ſhe will be eclipſed. And indeed in the <hi>Indies,</hi> not only Children, but rational illiterate Men, could not perceive, how 'twas poſſible for the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropeans</hi> to converſe with one another by the help of a piece of Paper, at an hundred Miles diſtance, and in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment produce Thunder and Lightning, and kill Men a great way off, as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48436:95"/>they ſaw Gunners and Muſqueteers do, and much leſs foretell an Eclipſe of the Moon, as <hi>Columbus</hi> did to his great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; which things made the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> even the chiefeſt of them, look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as perſons of a more than <hi>humane</hi> Nature. Now among thoſe that have a true Notion of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is a Being both omnipotent and omniſcient; That he can do all, and more than all, that is poſſible to be performed by any way of diſpoſing of Matter and Motion, is a Truth, that will be readily acknowledged, ſince he was able at firſt to produce the world, and contrive ſome part of the univerſal Matter of it into the Bodies of the firſt Man and Woman. And that his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er extends to the Re-union of a Soul and Body that have been ſeparated by Death, we may learn from the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments God has been pleaſed to give of it both in the Old Teſtament and the New, eſpecially in the raiſing again to life <hi>Lazarus</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> of the latter of which particularly we have Proofs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent enough to ſatisfie any unprejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Perſon, that deſires but competent Arguments to convince him. And that the miraculous Power of God will be,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48436:96"/>as well as his Veracity is, engaged in rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up the Dead, and may ſuffice if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be ſo, we may not difficultly gathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from that excellent Admonition of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Saviour to the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> where he tell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them, (as I elſewhere noted) that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> two Cauſes of their Errors are, their no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> knowing the <hi>Scriptures</hi> wherein God hath declared he <hi>will</hi> raiſe the Dead, nor the <hi>Power of God,</hi> by which he <hi>is able</hi> to effect it. But the engagement of Gods Omnipotence is alſo in that place clearly intimated by St. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 26.8. where he asks King <hi>Agrippa</hi> and his other Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, why they ſhould think it a thing not to be believed (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,) that GOD ſhould raiſe the Dead. And the ſame Truth is yet more fully expreſt by the ſame Apoſtle, where ſpeaking of Chriſt returning in the Glory and Power of his Father to judge all Mankind, after he has ſaid, that this divine Judge ſhall transform or transfigure (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) <hi>our vile Bodies</hi> (ſpeaking of his own, and thoſe of other Saints,) to ſubjoin the Account on which this ſhall be done, he adds, <hi>that 'twill be according to the powerful working</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) <hi>whereby he is able even to ſubdue all things to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> Phil. 3.21.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48436:96"/>
                  <p>And now 'twill be ſeaſonable to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what has been deliver'd in the whole paſt Diſcourſe to our preſent purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since</hi> then a Humane Body is not ſo confin'd to a determinate Bulk, but that the ſame Soul being united to a portion of duly organized Matter, is ſaid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the ſame Man, notwithſtanding the vaſt differences of bigneſs that there may be at ſeveral times between the portions of Matter whereto the Humane Soul is united:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since</hi> a conſiderable part of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body conſiſts of Bones which are Bodies of a very determinate Nature, and not apt to be deſtroyed by the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration either of Earth or Fire:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since</hi> of the leſs ſtable, and eſpecially the fluid parts of a Humane Body there is a far greater expence made by inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Tranſpiration than even Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers would imagine:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since</hi> the ſmall Particles of a reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Body may retain their own Nature under various alterations and diſguiſes, of which 'tis poſſible they may be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſtript:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since,</hi> without making a Humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ceaſe to be the ſame, it may be repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and augmented by the adaptation of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48436:97"/>congruouſly diſpoſed Matter to that which pre-exiſted in it:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Since,</hi> I ſay, theſe things are ſo, why ſhould it be impoſſible, that a moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Agent, whoſe Omnipotency ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to all that is not truly contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to the nature of things, or to his own, ſhould be able ſo to order and watch the Particles of a Humane Body, as that <hi>partly</hi> of thoſe that remain in the Bones, and <hi>partly</hi> of thoſe that copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly flie away by inſenſible Tranſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and <hi>partly</hi> of thoſe that are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſpoſed of upon their reſolution, a competent number may be preſerved or retrieved; ſo that ſtripping them of their diſguiſes, or extricating them from other parts of Matter, to which they may happen to be conjoined, he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite them betwixt themſelves, and, if need be, with particles of Matter fit to be contexted with them, and thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore or reproduce a Body, which, being united with the former Soul, may, in a ſenſe conſonant to the expreſſions of Scripture, recompoſe the ſame Man, whoſe Soul and Body were formerly disjoined by Death.</p>
                  <p>What has been hitherto diſcours'd, ſuppoſes the Doctrine of the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:48436:97"/>to be taken in a more ſtrict and lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſenſe, becauſe I would ſhew, that even according to that, the difficulties of anſwering what is mentioned againſt the poſſibility of it are not inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; though I am not ignorant, that it would much facilitate the defence and explication of ſo abſtruſe a thing, if their opinion be admitted, that allow themſelves a greater latitude in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the Article of the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as if the ſubſtance of it were: That, in regard the <hi>Humane Soul</hi> is the form of Man, ſo that whatever duly organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed portion of Matter 'tis united to, it therewith conſtitutes the ſame Man, the import of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> is fulfilled in this, that after Death there ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſtate, wherein the Soul ſhall no longer perſevere in its ſeparate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or, as it were, Widowhood, but ſhall be again united not to an etherial or the like fluid Matter, but to ſuch a ſubſtance as may, with tolerable propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of ſpeech, notwithſtanding its dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences from our <hi>houſes of Clay</hi> (as the Scripture ſpeaks) be call'd a Humane Body.
<note place="margin">Job 4.19.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>They that aſſent to what has been hitherto diſcours'd of the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48436:98"/>the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the ſame Bodies, will, I preſume, be much more eaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y induc'd to admit the Poſſibility of the Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations the Chriſtian Religion aſcribes to the <hi>glorified</hi> Bodies of the raiſed Saints. For, ſuppoſing the Truth of the Hiſtory of the Scriptures, we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that the Power of God has alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy extended itſelf to the performance of ſuch things as import as much as we need infer, ſometimes by ſuſpending the natural actings of Bodies upon one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and ſometimes by endowing hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and other Bodies with preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Qualities. And indeed Lightneſs, or rather Agility, indifferent to Gravity and Levity, Incorruption, Tranſparen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Opacity, Figure, Colour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being but Mechanical affections of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it cannot be incredible, that the moſt free and powerful Author of thoſe Laws of Nature, according to which all the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of Qualities are regulated, may (as he thinks fit) introduce, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, or change them in any aſſign'd portion of Matter, and conſequently in that whereof a Humane Body conſiſts. Thus, though Iron be a Body above eight times heavier, bulk for bulk, than Water, yet, in the caſe of <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s helve,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48436:98"/>its native Gravity was render'd ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, and it emerg'd from the bottom to the top of the water: And the gravita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Body was ſuſpended, whilſt his Maſter commanded him, and by that command enabled him, to come to him walking on the Sea. Thus the Operation of the activeſt Body in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Flame,</hi> was ſuſpended in <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi>'s fiery Furnace, whilſt <hi>Daniels</hi> three Companions walked unharm'd in thoſe Flames, that in a trice conſum'd the kindlers of them. Thus did the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites Manna,</hi> which was of ſo periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a Nature, that it would corrupt in little above a day, when gather'd in any day of the Week but that which prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Sabbath, keep good twice as long, and when laid up before the Ark for a Memorial, would laſt whole Ages uncorrupted. And to add a Proof, that comes more directly home to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the Body of our Saviour after his Reſurrection, though it retained the very impreſſions, that the Nails of the Croſs had made in his hands and feet, and the wound, that the Spear had made in his ſide, and was ſtill call'd in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture his Body, as indeed it was, and more ſo, than, according to our paſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48436:99"/>diſcourſe, it is neceſſary that every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould be that is rejoin'd to the Soul in the Reſurrection: And yet this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Body had the ſame Qualifications, that are promiſed to the Saints in their ſtate of Glory; St. <hi>Paul</hi> informing us, <hi>that our vile. Bodies ſhall be transform'd into the likeneſs of</hi> his <hi>glorious Body,</hi> which the Hiſtory of the Goſpel aſſures us was endow'd with far nobler Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties than before its Death. And whereas the Apoſtle adds, as we formerly noted, that this great change of Schematiſm in the Saints Bodies will be effected by the <hi>irreſiſtible Power of Chriſt,</hi> we ſhall not much ſcruple at the admiſſion of ſuch an effect from ſuch an Agent, if we conſider how much the bare ſlight Mechanical alteration of the Texture of a Body may change its ſenſible Qualities for the better. For without any viſible addita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I have ſeveral times chang'd dark and opacous Lead into finely colour'd tranſparent and ſpecifically lighter glaſs. And there is another inſtance, which, though becauſe of its obviouſneſs 'tis leſs heeded, is yet more conſiderable: For who will diſtruſt, what advantageous changes ſuch an Agent as God can work by changing the Texture of a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48436:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Matter, if he but obſerve, what happens meerly upon the account of ſuch a Mechanical change in the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Candle that is newly blown out by the applying another to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending ſmoke. For in the twinkling of an Eye, an opacous, dark, languid an ſtinking ſmoke loſes all its ſtink, and is changed into a moſt active penetrant and ſhining Body.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
